<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plea for Christian magistracie: or, An answer to some passages in Mr. Gillespies sermon, against Mr. Coleman. As also to the brotherly examination of some passages of Mr. Colemans late printed sermon, upon Job 11.20. In which the reverend and learned commissioner affirmeth, he hath endeavoured to strike at the root of all church government. VVherein the argumentative part of the controversie is calmely and mildly, without any personall reflections, prosecuted. / By William Hussey, minister of the Gospell, at Chesilhurst in Kent.</title>
            <author>Hussey, William, minister of Chiselhurst.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3819</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E313_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200474</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861207</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861207</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113335</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113335)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 51:E313[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plea for Christian magistracie: or, An answer to some passages in Mr. Gillespies sermon, against Mr. Coleman. As also to the brotherly examination of some passages of Mr. Colemans late printed sermon, upon Job 11.20. In which the reverend and learned commissioner affirmeth, he hath endeavoured to strike at the root of all church government. VVherein the argumentative part of the controversie is calmely and mildly, without any personall reflections, prosecuted. / By William Hussey, minister of the Gospell, at Chesilhurst in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Hussey, William, minister of Chiselhurst.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Saywell, and are to bee sold at his shop at the signe of the Starre in Little Brittaine,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646 [i.e. 1645]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Thomason received his copy December 20, 1645; Wing has 1646; McAlpin Catalogue lists under 1646.</note>
                  <note>Part of a controversy which included George Gillespie and Thomas Coleman.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 20 1645"; the second 6 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gillespie, George, 1613-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Coleman, Thomas, 1598-1647. --  Hopes deferred and dashed.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="prefatory_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:113335:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113335:1"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, the Lords <hi>and Commons aſſembled in Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, I have ever thought it the duty of us Miniſters to debate matters of doctrine, which is <hi>jus divinum,</hi> amongſt our ſelves, ſo as that wee might all agree in the things that ſhould be taught among the people; which bleſſing of unity, would certainly in a great meaſure be granted to us of God, if we were ſet in ſuch a ſtation that we might uſe the means (which were Schools of Divinity:) were we ſet into Claſſes, and from our youth kept in the exerciſe of Divinity diſputation, before we were ſwaied with ambitious ends, truth would in a great meaſure appeare to us, which is now hid: truth is but one, the Goſpell is the Goſpell of peace: it is our ignorance of truth and of the Goſpell, that maketh us at ſuch diſtance in opinions: now there is no ſuch meanes in all the world to acquire knowledge, as diſputation: therefore is that art which hath truth for its end, ſtudied, and gotten in Schooles of Diſputation: I meane Logick, Rhetoricke is <hi>ornatus,</hi> the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or ornament of ſpeech. Now though perſons of greateſt quality doe uſually weare the richeſt garments, yet garments of greateſt value may be borrowed, and put upon the pooreſt ſlave and vileſt begger: the falſeſt and leaſt probable matter is capable of curious ornament of words, where it is a matter of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt skill in the world to find out the truth, among theſe colours of Rhetoricke: and thoſe things that ought not to be taught, will moſt forcibly draw diſciples after their teachers. At this time, ye may heere the Pulpits filled with eager and earneſt perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to accept of the government of Chriſt, ſet up in the word of God, without any argument out of Gods word, to proove that Chriſt ſet up any ſuch government as they aime at.</p>
            <p>If any argument can be produced, it is fit we all ſhould know it: and if ſo the word of God, and the authority of Chriſt, muſt
<pb facs="tcp:113335:2"/>not be bounded by any authority on earth; no power among the ſonnes of men may limit the Holy One of Iſraell.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt hath ſet officers in his Church, Kings and Nobles and Senators muſt ſtoop to them: this intermixing of the Parliament authority, with divine, is but dawbing, if it be any other then an acknowledgement of duty of ſubmiſſion, if Chriſt hath ſet up any government in his Church to be executed by Church officers.</p>
            <p>As for giving leave to execute diſcipline, as to preach the word, that is but a fraud; you may indeed, nay you ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the word of God not for your ſelves alone, but for the whole Nation, as being the Repreſentative Body thereof: you may require a Covenant over all the Kingdome to wait on the means not by pieces and parcells, but the whole word which ought to have a free paſſage, not by plurality of votes, but by an unanimous conſent of the Preachers.</p>
            <p>That the word ought to be ſo preached, is plaine by theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Chriſt gave a Commiſſion to preach the Goſpell unto his diſciples, which was to laſt unto the end of the world, in which there was no <hi>Quorum, duobus tribus vel pluribus veſtrum,</hi> by which they might not preach but by an univerſall conſent.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall object, that the Apoſtles walked by an higher prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple even by the ducture of an infallible ſpirit.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, firſt the Commiſſion was penned in words that muſt laſt to the end of the world by which we muſt walke.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The infallibility of the Spirit by which the Apoſtles wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, did imply an impoſſibility of diſſent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though the Apoſtles did know that it was impoſſible for them to diſagree in their doctrine, yet St. Paul went up by the Spirit to communicate his doctrine to other of the Apoſtles James and Peter, leſt in regard of the people he had run in vain; hee knew the unity of the Preachers would prevaile much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people. Gal. 2.2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, St. Paul wrote to Timothy to charge thoſe that taught any other doctrine that they ſhould not, whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that he had a care that no other doctrine might be taught but one. 1 Tim. 1.3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt promiſed his preſence among two or three that are
<pb facs="tcp:113335:2"/>gathered together in his name, he promiſed nothing to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of ſuch an aſſembly: this gathering together cannot bee underſtood of a locall, but a gathering by the Spirit into an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of minde and judgement: Chriſts promiſes attend on the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of our duties, when we doe our duties we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a bleſſing. St. Paul to the Corinthians, 1 Cor. 1.10. beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth them by the name of our Lord Jeſus, that they all ſpeake the ſame thing, that there be no diviſions among them, but that they bee perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde, and the ſame judgement; where you ſee he urgeth them by the name, by the reverence and honour that they beare to the name of Chriſt, that they be of one minde: thoſe that are gathered together in the name of Chriſt are of one minde; I doe not ſay, that all thoſe to the number of two or three that are of one minde are gathered in the name of Chriſt: nay the gathering in the name is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced from other ambitious and hereticall gatherings, <hi>cumulo accidentium,</hi> whereof this being of one minde is one; ſuch a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering together is worthy the preſence of Chriſt, ſeldome can many agree in one judgement that Chriſt doth not unite in any thing that tendeth to the glory of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Some may ſay that it is impoſſible that men ſhould be all of one minde ſo much diviſion is found among us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> I anſwer, that this unity hath not beene ſought after, means have not been uſed for the obtaining it: all things have been carried by vote, and the diſſenting party kept under by cenſure, accompained with fire and ſword under Antichriſtian Tyranny: the truth was kept under by the vote of the ambitious, and Schooles wholly, neglected, or uſed only <hi>more imperato;</hi> queſtions not ſtated by Scripture, but the Scripture overſwayed by humane authority.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe I conceive it neceſſary for Claſſes and Aſſemblies to meet, but their buſineſſe is only about matters of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, about preaching the word, to communicate their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and by diſpute to finde out the truth: their diſputes ought to end in a brotherly accord, as in Act. 15. much diſputing, but all ended in accord, no putting to the vote.</p>
            <p>Votes have too great an influence upon the will to decide matters of doctrine by them: men may vote what they have an
<pb facs="tcp:113335:3"/>intereſt to diſpoſe of, I may vote my eſtate and liberty, but will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip is unlawfull: I meane the matters that are eſſentiall to Gods worſhip which are matters of duty, as for circumſtantialls of time and place (except the Sabbath) which are matters of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; in theſe things the Commonwealth may vote, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters muſt by the duty of their place preach the Goſpell when and where they can get any to heare in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon; &amp; this is your Chriſtian liberty that in matters of liberty, ye make rules and laws to your ſelves, not croſſing the ends that you are tyed to in duty: but if Aſſemblies of Miniſters might make Canons, and bind men to obedience under penalty of excommunication; what were this other then to Lord it over the flocke? or what were this, if not teaching for doctrines the precepts of men? but this is endeavoured to be amended by intermixing of Lay-elders what ground they have for that, will, I hope, appear if the whole matter come into juſt concertation by dint of argument.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, if the State thinke fit to ſuffer the Aſſembly to vote what they doe is but humane, one good reaſon is better then many votes in matters of doctrine, and matters of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it wholy belongeth to the Civill Magiſtrate, this ſhould be rightly conſidered on; what is Chriſts cannot bee remitted to you if by him placed in other hands; if he hath ſet up government in the Church, it muſt be far above all government in a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Commonwealth: and it were ſacriledge of the higheſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for you to reſtraine Chriſts officers by any power; if you put the matter to vote in the Aſſembly, they will hereafter tell you of it in both ears. But if ye deſire to know the truth, by that time Schooles of Divinity be up but halfe the time the Aſſembly have ſat, ye ſhall finde more the preſent condition of things, require your preſent action.</p>
            <p>You may, you ought to covenant for the whole Kingdome, for time, place, and maintenance of Gods worſhip: you have (as the great Sanhedrim of the Kingdome) power to judge of falſe worſhip: you may make uſe of the ſword to drive out Idolatry and will worſhip, and accordingly may require all men in the Kingdome, to come to the ſeverall Pariſh Churches of their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode, and require ſuch as you receive for the Preachers of truth, to ſend able men to ſupply the places, and that without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb facs="tcp:113335:3"/>to the allowance and diſallowance of the people. I know theſe be the great queſtions of the times, and high time it is the truth were knowne concerning them.</p>
            <p>It is time ſome courſe were taken to bring men to Church, which Independent principles make ſcruple, whether the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ought to doe, unleſſe they like their Miniſter: but upon this ground, let the Miniſter be who he will, the Drunkard will like the Alehouſe better then the Church: and this liberty that men take to abſent themſelves from their Pariſh Churches, give men opportunity to meet and rayſe tumults, plots, ſeditions; and how dangerous theſe things may ſpeedily be, if not prevented, let wiſe men judge. Oh that this Honourable Court would ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to ſet up Claſſes conſiſting only of Miniſters, whoſe worke ſhould be only to preach the word, and weekly meet in Schools of Divinity, where they might not ſpend their times in exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Whores and Knaves, ye may take another courſe with them: but let them diſpute, and nurſe up yong Scholers, who being firſt made artiſts in the Univerſities, they may be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with, and not lay hands raſhly upon a teſtimony, and ſo ſend them out to places that want: and as for government, you know ſure, that to come to Church is a duty neglect, a ſin and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; and what elſe the Miniſters know cenſurable, you know aſ well as they, and you ought to puniſh: but having firſt ſet down the ſin and puniſhment, not at the diſcretion of the Miniſter and his two Elders, which yet ought to be according to the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian principles.</p>
            <p>Only for matter of knowledge, that of all things principally belongeth to the care of the Miniſter: and I could wiſh before this Aſſembly were diſſolved, a cleere and full Catechiſme were agreed on, ſhort and pithy, that might be required of all commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants in the Kingdome, old and yong, high and low, and all compelled to it by your authority, that ſo the ſame thing might be taught throughout the whole Kingdome.</p>
            <p>As for Independents and Anabaptiſts, let them be admitted, nay condemned to ſpend their times in Schooles, and not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſeduce the people, that ſo at laſt all things may be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with ſtrength of argument, and unanimous conſent of the whole Clergy, which would ſoone come amongſt them, if they
<pb facs="tcp:113335:4"/>did not relie on their parties and drawing diſciples, and deciding matters by votes.</p>
            <p>Againe, votes are of no other uſe, but to gather parties, and ought no where to be uſed but by thoſe that have power of the ſword, to compell the diſſenting parties, and therefore are penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to terrifie and keepe under the diſſenting part annexed to ſuch lawes as paſſe by vote. I pray God it be not in the minde of ſome of our times to get parties, and put the carrying on their ends by the determination of the ſword. A learned and pious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery doe not deſire to carry all by vote, but a lazie, ambitious, proud Clergie: an induſtrious, learned, wait with patience on them that are contrary minded for the day of Gods viſitation, in the meane time uſe all means: the proud man will take no paines to uſe means but vote him downe, away with him to the divell; it is fault enough to croſſe them, ſuch as ſtand in their waies are fooles and knaves not fit to be heard or conſulted with; let it be conſidered whether parties in Generall Councells, have not made parties for the ſword: I am a ſtranger to the State whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they doe not make parties among Lords and Commons, if they doe not, I pray God they may not, I know it is very farre from the duties of their places that ought to be peace-makers.</p>
            <p>Learning is low, and pride is high among the Clergy, I ſpeake not this with reference to what any mans particular diligence hath made him; yet I dare ſay, every honeſt man will confeſſe, had all the Kingdome beene exerciſed in Schooles of Divinity ſince the Reformation, where <hi>ipſe dixit</hi> had been the word of God, a great difference would have been in Miniſters from what they are.</p>
            <p>I know men uſe to ſay, Learning is not ſo needfull as holines: I anſwer, it is not an holy thing for a Miniſter not to uſe all means to be learned; holineſſe and learning will doe well together.</p>
            <p>But an holy Miniſter ought not adminiſter the Sacrament to a wicked perſon: I confeſſe there was a time in my youth that I thought ſo, and being preſſed to doe it, did uſe all means to make them as knowing as I could, which I conceive ſtill to bee my duty, but not able ſufficiently to ſatisfie my ſelfe in point of manner: I found <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſine</hi> and others, ſay, that if I were carefull to preſent notorious offenders to them that had power, I had
<pb facs="tcp:113335:4"/>done my duty, yet ſtill me thought I was not clean handed, if the duty lay upon me to examine and try the due preparation of the receiver.</p>
            <p>But upon further conſideration, I found the Miniſter charged only with preaching and baptizing, which being performed with ſuch zeal and diligence as is needfull, is abundantly a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient imployment.</p>
            <p>Objection: ought not the Miniſter to have regard to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of his flocke? may all come without reſpect, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo wicked and unholy, and be partaker of Sacraments?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> I anſwer, they may not, it is a very great and dangerous ſin if they come without repentance, faith and charity, wherein the Miniſter muſt inſtruct his people publiquely and privately, and that with anſwerable zeale to the ignorance and ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the people; he muſt preach the duty of the Magiſtrate to him: firſt, to make lawes that may compell all men to a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent attendance on the means if he be a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, if he be not a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, he muſt endeavour his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: when wholeſome and holy laws are made, he muſt inſtantly call upon that Magiſtrate that is put in truſt to puniſh ſin, that he put wholeſome lawes in execution to put ſin to ſhame; that as ſin is a work of darkneſſe, ſo no man may preſume to commit it in the ſight of the Sun: if this were done, what ſcandall could be given to the Church if any ſhould be found guilty before and after receiving Sacraments, the Law may appoint that a double puniſhment, as being a double offence? in ſome caſes reſtraine him of his liberty to come to Sacraments as the Law ſhall bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on: in the meane time, let the Miniſter plye both the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate and offender with the mighty operative word of God, private Chriſtians uſing their private intereſt to reclaim the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. If this be not the way of God, I am miſtaken, if any further power can be proved out of Gods word to be in the hand of the Miniſter, I ſhall be content to uſe it: In the mean time, let no man that hath voted himſelfe high, or hath gotten a great opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among men, deſpiſe arguments that come from an obſcurer perſon: I conceive the Miniſter may uſe, nay muſt, any ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the word uſeth againſt ſin, and then betake himſelfe to his prayers to God to make his doctrine fruitfull: what more is in
<pb facs="tcp:113335:5"/>the duty of his place, I know not, unleſſe uſing of means to make him able to doe that: if this be not a meanes to ſhame and cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell ſin to corners, I know not what can. But ſuppoſe the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate doth not doe his duty, then let the Miniſter bend the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the word upon him, and no doubt if Miniſters could agree in their doctrine, much would be the power of the word: We ſee the Magiſtrate come and ſit before us, and wee hope with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an Idoll in their hearts. Oh that the Lord would put a word in due ſeaſon into the mouth of his Miniſters, that might bee the word of peace unto them!</p>
            <p>Oh that Miniſters, would lay downe the rigor of their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in point of Diſcipline, and ſet themſelves to attend on the meanes to increaſe their knowledge, and to acquaint themſelves with one anothers ſtudies in an induſtrious way, that they would unbend their thought of government a while, and thinke on waies to get knowledge; I am not worthy to cenſure others, I know my owne defects, and doe complaine of the times and want of means to know more: I wiſh that all men of skill would examine what Logick may be found in many of thoſe Rethori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Sermons which the world ſo much run after, how well the Divinity of many of them is taught that are ſo finely worded; how right they hit the argument of their text, which if they miſſe, they preach themſelves and not Chriſt, their own minds and not the minde of God: nay let men of piety examine whether Mr. <hi>Gillespie,</hi> though a man of excellent parts, proved his reformation by his Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline out of the words of his text, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that refiners fire and fullers ſope doth not point at another and a nearer operation upon the ſoules and ſpirits of men by the bloud of Chriſt, then his Reformation that he ſo eagerly preſſeth, and then ſee whether we want not Schooles; if men of his parts want them, <hi>Sanctius, hoc vero Chriſti doctrina facit:</hi> and citeth Jer. 23.29. to prove the purgation by doctrine and operation of the word, Is not my word an hammer: And <hi>Clement Alexandirnus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Theodoret, <hi>divina gratia, tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> herba peceatorum ſordes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luit.</hi> Let it be further examined whether the choice of a ſimilitude for a text which is but illuſtrative, &amp; draw what men fancie out of the ſimilitude, and paſſing by the argumentative part, be to preach
<pb facs="tcp:113335:5"/>the minde of God, or mens owne fancie, whether this Rethori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call liberty do fill all the world with ſuch diverſities of opinions. Ornament of words call weake judgement to admiration, but incumber the truth, if not imbezell and ſteale it quite away, whereas ſtrength of argument doth inform the judgement; men talke much of having their affections wrought upon; theſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be wrought upon to ſalvation, but by the ſtill voice of the Spirit: I deny not, but fine words and ſmooth cadencies of ſentences, may worke naturally upon the affections, but the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of it is but as the blade that ſprang up in ſtony ground, ſuch Religion unto which men are led by the eloquence of the Preacher when it ſhall bee charged with greater triall then na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will beare, their affection that were led with naturall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light will ſinke under the diſquietneſſe of nature: I condemne not Rethoricke, but ſuſpect it and wiſh it may bee well cemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with judgement, and not uſed to ſuch that have no skill to deceive themſelves, and them that heare them; let the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſet us to our worke, puniſh us for our idleneſſe, and afford ſuch incouragement by publique laws that men of choiſeſt parts may be induced to the worke of the Miniſtery: thoſe that would perſwade you that publique proviſion ought not to be made for preaching the Goſpell by tythes or otherwiſe, would make all Nations, heathen and Idolaters, not to have any publique inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the Goſpell; thoſe would have the State alwaies to ſtand at defiance with Religion. The Lord grant Aſſemblies, Parliaments to be at one among themſelves, and one with another. Thoſe therefore that cannot agree among themſelves cannot be ſaid to bring the Goſpell; thoſe that allow diverſities of opinions, and claim a liberty to preach what they liſt: I wiſh that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would ſet up but one learned School of Divinty, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the principall patrons of that Independent opinion into thoſe Schooles, where they ſhould do exerciſe among others, I make no queſtion they would be ſoon converted or confounded, and left without any word to ſay in defence of that groundleſſe doctrine. I had good hope that they would have agreed in the Aſſembly, after two years diſpute; I could have been content with ſmall faults if piety and peace might have been ſettled. I hope there be witneſſes enough that I ſet them not at odds, I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make them friends, if reaſon will doe it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſervant, <hi>W. Huſſey.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113335:6"/>
            <head>To the Right VVorſhipfull Sir <hi>Thomas Walſingham,</hi> Knight.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am bold to Dedicate the firſt fruits of my Labours in this kinde unto your view and patronage, unto whom <hi>I</hi> know the intention is not unwelcome, as ayming at the conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the State and Miniſters of the Word in peace and unity, that hitherto have beene kept at diſtance by theſe dividing principles, ariſing from a twofold diſtinct government, which being agreed on to be but one (and <hi>I</hi> hope to make appeare they ought not to bee divers) would for ever ſilence thoſe implacable differences that have long time beene betweene them, and remaine a hard matter to reconcile at this time. Sir, <hi>I</hi> have ever obſerved your aime to be at peace, and justice to keepe of violence and oppreſſion from all men, ſo farre as your trust and imployment (which hath beene great, in and for your Country) would inable you; <hi>I</hi> aime at the ſame ends, both to make the Parliament and Miniſters all agree, and all ayme at Gods glory, and the Countries ſafety, wherein <hi>I</hi> know no man would more rejoyce then your ſelfe. <hi>I</hi> confeſſe the firſt ſound of this my opinion out of the mouth of Maſter <hi>Coleman,</hi> was very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome to our brethren, and <hi>I</hi> look for no better entertaynment. I have ſome incouragement, that a man ſo eminent is gone before me, and doe hope that upon ſome pauſe they may receive better ſatisfactions, and that at they were forwards but Biſhops might bee plucked up root and branch, ſo they will at laſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to plucke up this root of their
<pb facs="tcp:113335:6"/>ſpirituall cenſure, upon which the ſtate and ambition of the Biſhops was firſt planted, I ſhall not deſire to engage you in defence of the cauſe; but if any good come by it to the Kingdome, that you ſhould enjoy the benefit: unto whoſe happineſſe here, and eternall, my duty doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage mee to boſtow my ſelfe, and all the abilities God hath given mee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord, VVIL. HUSSEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prefatory_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:113335:7"/>
            <head>To the Reverend Commiſsioner of <hi>Scotland, Mr.</hi> George Gilleſpie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, The eminencie of your imployment, and my obſcurity, may make the congreſſe between us ſeem unequall: my calling is the ſame with yours: my education hath been the education of a Scholler, though with leſſe proficiencie then I could wiſh: you profeſſe candor in attending to, and anſwering arguments: It may be ſome of my arguments may ſeeme weake unto you, I feare they may ſome of them be weaker then I could wiſh: I confeſſe I cannot urge an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as it ought to be urged, the want of Divinity Schools hath been the cauſe of it: joyne with me in your petition for Divinity Schools, then you and I ſhall know better how to handle an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument at 7 years end then now we doe, if we live ſo long: In the mean time, if you ſhew me the weakneſſe of my argument, I ſhall not endeavour to maintain it againſt light of truth, no not ſo far as any ſtrain of wit will bear me; if your anſwers ſhew any thing I did not conſider of, I will acknowledge it: hee that knoweth nothing of an argument is too ignorant to be a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, he that will not ſubmit to an argument out of Gods word &amp; principles of nature, is to proud to be a Miniſter; unity among our ſelves would be an happy thing, and an indiſſoluble amity between us and the Gentry were of great concernment: in theſe times, we have need of them, and they of us, let us endeavour to make uſe of our friends, and not make them our foes; I perſwade not any man to depart from truth to pleaſe men; but let us not wreſtle with our friends for that which is not, while our enemies deſtroy us; thogh our judgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts differ, yet let us diſpute as friends and agree as ſoon as may be. If any bitternes come from me I ſhal be ſorry and amend it; if any from you, I have been bred under Biſhops, I have been uſed to it, and can the better beare it, I ſhall overcome it with goodnes, if I can prevail with my corruptions to give way: The Lord grant that we may ſpeak the ſame thing, that there be no diviſions among us, that we be perfectly joyned in the ſame mind, and the ſame judgement: let there be no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention among us, we are brethren.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113335:7"/>
            <p>You ſay we have leave from the Civill Magiſtrate to preach the Goſpell: that was a Canterburian tenet to put doctrine and diſcipline into the ſame condition, and hold all under him, but we preach the word with all authority from Chriſt derived to us by thoſe of our brethren that were in commiſſion before us: Magiſtrates may drive away falſe teachers, but not the Preachers of the Goſpell, but at their uttermoſt perills.</p>
            <p>Let us ſtand to our commiſſion, and attend on reading, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and doctrine, and we may obtaine from the Magiſtrates in a fair way as a teſtimony of their love, honour and obedience to Chriſt, more honour, more maintenance, and ſin will be more ſhamed, diſcountenanced and puniſhed; Ordinances kept more pure in your ſenſe then ever you ſhall be able to procure by your ſcaring, affrighting cenſure of excommunication.</p>
            <p>What will your cenſure doe? it will ſhame a few whores and knaves; a great matter to ſhame them, the law of Nature ſhameth: a boy in the ſtreets can doe as much. But if your cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure work upon hereticks, or men differing from you in opinion; can you fetch in Antinomians, Anabaptiſts, Independents, if ye could ſend out Sathan and fetch them in, or by delivering them to Sathan, reclaime them, ſome reverence might be given to the cenſure? ſure in the day of our Lord, there will be as good a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of the word preached, as of the cenſure.</p>
            <p>But all this is nothing, if Chriſt hath ſet up any ſuch governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, prove that, I yeeld: My deſire is, that you would draw your arguments from the words of Scripture, and not from the interpretation, that you or any Authors ſhall put upon them, nor counter argue my arguments, without giving anſwers; in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering arguments you have liberty to interpret Scriptures as you pleaſe, ſo as your interpretation will ſtand out againſt all ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments that ſhall be brought againſt it: the ſtrength of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is in <hi>mediums</hi> conſiſting of termes and words of Scripture: where divine authority is pleaded, keep rules, and truth will ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner be found.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving Brother,
<hi>Will. Huſſey.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prefatory_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:113335:8"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He replies Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> touching this point in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie are publique. That which is perſonal in them (as a great part is) hath already, and ſhall preſently further be cleared. The argumentative part was purpoſely referred hither, which calmely and mildly, without any perſonall reflections is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted. A like candor and ingenuity is requeſted from all, that omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting accidentall ſlips (for ſuch poſſibly in acurſory reading may be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver looked) they would addreſſe themſelves to the maine, and clearly confute theſe aſſertions, or by Scripturall arguments confirme the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary poſitions; for if otherwiſe, and as heretofore, the argument be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, and perſonall charges of Covenant-breaking-diſſenting from the Aſſembly, not diſſenting in the Aſſembly, and ſuch like, be taken up: It is here declared before hand, all ſuch replications ſhall be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by us a <hi>Nihil Reſpondes:</hi> In the meane ſpace, read and judge, having no other by as upon thy heart, but that of the Prophet, an ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to follow truth and peace.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Th. Coleman.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 3. line 21. read mutation. p. 7. l. 3. r. theſe. p. 12. l. 14. adde to. l. 34. r. ſew.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113335:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Plea for</hi> Chriſtian Magiſtracie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aſter <hi>Gillespie</hi> ſeemeth in his Sermon to be much offended at Mr. <hi>Coleman:</hi> and telleth the Lords, the ignorant and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous muſt be kept from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, and with a flood of words, layeth on them as a very great ſin if they doe it not by adding diſcipline to this Doctrine that is already taught in the Directory, That ſcandalous and ignorant ought not to receive the Sacrament, and therefore the Miniſter in the name of Chriſt muſt warne ſuch that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume not to come: That the power of diſcipline may be added to the power of Doctrine: For my part I thinke it very derogatory to the word of God, and the commiſſion of Chriſt, to think that any cenſure of man, ſhould bee of more power and efficacy then the word of God: The authority of the Word is divine, the operation of it is mighty, the effect of it is perfection, it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth upon the conſcience, and if the word be able to make the man of God perfect, then nothing is wanting to him. <hi>Perfectum cui nihil deeſt:</hi> and it is a wonder how that conſcience ſhould be wrought upon by humane authority, with whom divine cannot prevaile; his arguments are, the ſcandalous perfons have profaned the Lords Table, and the Church of God ſhall be diſabled to keep
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113335:9"/>themſelves pure, if diſcipline be not ſet up to keep the ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous from the Lords Table, implying that wicked men by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Sacrament do pollute the Sacrament, and pollute the holy; which he doth not prove, but ſome others doe endeavour to doe out of 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.17. becauſe the ſinfull carriage of <hi>Elies</hi> ſonnes cauſed men to abhor the offering of the Lord: but note the reaſon that the offering became abominable, was becauſe they offered not the ſacrifice according to the command of God, they would not have ſodden fleſh, but raw; if the doctrine of the Sacrament be corrupted, if it be celebrated under one kinde, if water be mingled with wine, if tranſubſtantiation be taught, or if adoration of the elements, this is to pollute the Ordinance: and therefore <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11. S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth command not to have felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the unfruitfull works of darknes, not workers of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: I may not goe to Maſſe with the Papiſt, nor run with the ungodly unto the ſame exceſſe of riot, I may not be drunk with the drunkard, nor ſweare with the ſwearer, but if theſe come and heare, or receive Sacraments with the beleevers they pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute not the Sacrament to them, he that beleeveth eateth of this bread of life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.33. and this ſhall be made good to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever, though there were but one in the world; and this <hi>Beza</hi> himſelfe is inforced to confeſſe in his tract againſt <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> his words are, <hi>Bonis manere bona Sacramenta etiamſi qui mali aà eadem accedunt ab ſit ut inficiemur:</hi> The Sacraments remain effectuall to the good, though evill men come to them, farre be it from us to deny it. So that the Sacrament remaineth holy to the beleever, and they are pure notwithſtanding the unpreparedneſſe of the wicked: Let a man examin himſelfe, and ſo let him eat, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. But the Author would fix guilt of ſin upon the Miniſter, if any come and receive that is ſcandalous: <hi>a neceſſity is laid upon us, and woe be to us if we doe it:</hi> this he proveth not preſently, but after many rethoricall paſſages to the Lords, which deſerve no anſwer: he citeth the Story, and noteth the ſin of <hi>Ely,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.13. in that he reſtrained not his ſonnes, and thereupon telleth us out of <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> that we may conſent to other mens ſinnes; firſt directly counſelling or approving. Secondly, indirectly by not hindring when we can; but note; when we can muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this limitation, that is, when of duty we ought and can;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113335:9"/>otherwiſe a man ſhould be compelled to forſake his owne cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and watch him that he ſuſpected to be a thiefe, or a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, and get company and ſeize on them; and impriſon them to keepe them from offending, but this were to deny a free-man his liberty, and become a tranſgreſſour; all that is ſaid to this point is, That if it were the duty of the Miniſter and Elder to hinder a ſcandalous ſinner from the Sacrament, he were guilty of his ſin if he let him come: when that is proved, it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſome further anſwer; in the meane time, what is ſaid is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacious.</p>
            <p>But then a particular application againſt Mr. <hi>Coleman: he will neither be active nor paſſive in eſtabliſhing ſin cenſuring government:</hi> I dare promiſe for him that if any means be uſed for the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſinne, he ſhall endeavour the furtherance thereof; and if the State thinke fit to truſt him, hee will bee as faithfull as he that pleadeth moſt ſtoutly for the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall government; but here be high words, <hi>great offence and ſcandall is given;</hi> and the Author is confident <hi>every other godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter will ſay, Let my tongue cleave to the roofe of my mouth before I ſay the like.</hi> Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> ſcapeth very hardly being called knave, and in a rethoricall imitation of perſons curſed for his paines, <hi>let his tongue cleave,</hi> and in the beginning of his Tract, every mans hand is againſt Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> and his againſt every man; the world is made beleeve a Monſter is come abroad, if it be for his opinion only that all godly Miniſters will leave him they muſt leave others, whom Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> will not deny the eſtimation of godly Miniſters in their times. I ſhall be bold to name them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> ſhall not ſtand alone to be gazed at in theſe malitious times: they are <hi>Bullenger, Gualter, Muſculus, Zuinglius, Aretius, Eraſtus. Bullenger</hi> and <hi>Gualter,</hi> in their letters to <hi>Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> teſtifie as much, but becauſe thoſe letters were put forth by ſome favourer of <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> and therefore may ſeem to be without credit, I ſhall be bold to cite what <hi>Beza</hi> in his Preface to his Tract againſt <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> concerning <hi>Bullenger,</hi> and <hi>Gualter</hi> doth confeſſe, of whom he ſaith: I doe not at all deny the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of thoſe famous men, as alſo of <hi>Wolfgangus Muſculus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Minime tamen nego maximes illos viros ut &amp; Dominum <hi>Wolfgangum Muſculu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimaſſe excommunicationem penes Preſbyterium fuiſſe &amp; ad excluſionem uſque à Coena Domini Preſbyteros ideo fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe progreſſos. Quod Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianum tunc Magiſtratum non haberet Eccleſiacujus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate capitalia judicia exercerenter (quod ſi Corinthi factum fuiſſet nulla fuiſſet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus <hi>Pauli</hi> de illo, Sathanae tradendo denuntiatione) tum alii, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> levioribus offendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis peccantes citra excluſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem à coena ſatis coerceren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: quod cum utrumque praſtare Chriſtianus Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus, nunc poſſit ac debeat carere nunc poſſe Chriſtianas eccleſias hae diſciplinae ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</note> to bee thus, excommunication is in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113335:10"/>power of Presbytery, and that the Presbyters did proceed even to ſuſpenſion from the Lords Supper, becauſe the Church at that time had no Chriſtian Magiſtrate by whoſe authority capitall cenſures might be exerciſed (which if it had been uſed, there had been no need of <hi>Pauls</hi> delivery of the man to Sathan) and alſo other diſorderly men tranſgreſſing in ſmaller mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, might well enough be reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned without ſuſpenſion from the Sacrament: both which, becauſe the Chriſtian Magiſtrate now may and ought to doe, The Chriſtian Churches may wel be without this ſharpe diſcipline; thus much he confeſſeth, <hi>Sed it a ut neque Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae locos novis &amp; ad hanc ſuam ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam accommodatis interpretatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus applicarent.</hi> But ſo, as that they did not wreſt Scripture texts with interpretations new, and fitted to their opinion whereby it appeareth that theſe mens opinions were, that the words of S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 Cor. 5 were a denunciation of the ſentence of excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but occaſionall and particular; no univerſall precept, nor imitable by us, <hi>Niſi rebus omnimodo ſic ſtantibus,</hi> but in the like condition, and this is enough to daſh all contentions about the ſentence of excommunication, this makes all further diſpute meerly ſpeculative, we have a Chriſtian Civill Magiſtrate though the preſent differences have taken away much of our comfort we might enjoy in them, and theſe diſputes render them of leſſe uſe to us, and us to them; whatſoever they ſhall ſpeake concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſentence of excommunication upon the ſeverall places of Scripture, if they may ſtand with theſe words here acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by <hi>Beza,</hi> let theſe men without more contention ſtand on Mr <hi>Colemans</hi> part, if otherwiſe they muſt be underſtood upon after
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113335:10"/>thoughts to be bent about by <hi>Eraſtus</hi> his arguments, as <hi>Beza</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confeſſeth, <hi>Illos aliquantum in excommunicationis uſu &amp; Preſbyterii authoritate, non quod iſta per ſe damnarent, ſed quod co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum abuſum vererentur, ad Eraſti ſententiam de flexiſſe.</hi> That they did incline to the opinion of <hi>Eraſtus</hi> in the uſe of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and authority of the Presbytery, not becauſe they ſimply condemned them, but becauſe they feared their abuſe. You ſee theſe men did fear the abuſe, and though <hi>Beza</hi> will not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Eraſtus</hi> reaſon to be of any weight, yet with reaſon, or without he confeſſeth (take him in the mildeſt ſenſe) that they bent or leaned a little toward <hi>Eraſtus;</hi> at leaſt ſo far that in their Churches where they had to do they would not truſt the Geneva diſcipline; <hi>Beza</hi> himſelfe citeth theſe words out of an Epiſtle which he acknowledgeth to be <hi>Bullengers</hi> to <hi>Eraſtus, Neque putes nos ita eſſe dementes, ut hic omnia ad rigerem Genevenſis Eccleſiae exigere, aut revocare velimus.</hi> Neither doe thou thinke us to bee ſo mad that we would reduce all things to, and exact them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſtrict diſcipline of Geneva: and this not in <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingers</hi> owne name, but of the Tigurine Churches. I hope theſe men ſhall have Mr. <hi>Colemans</hi> favour, every other godly Miniſter will ſay, &amp;c. I ſhall ſay nothing to Mr. <hi>Gilleſpies</hi> Preamble.</p>
            <p>He excepteth againſt Mr. <hi>Colemans</hi> firſt rule, and ſeemeth to oppoſe a contrary rule, whereas indeed Mr. <hi>Colemans</hi> as little as may be, and his as much as may be, are both one: Mr. <hi>Colemans</hi> meaning is, that no more ſhould be eſtabliſhed then what was in the word, and his meaning is as much ſhould be eſtabliſhed as is in the word of God: this being doubtleſſe both your meanings, yee need not fall out about that, greater difference will ariſe.</p>
            <p>For my part, I thinke Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> underſtandeth Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> aright, that he thinketh that no Church cenſures in the hand of Church officers are found in the word of God: but I am nor or his minde, <hi>ex ſuppoſito</hi> that they are <hi>jure divine,</hi> and in the word of God, that he, or any Miniſter ought to be ſatisfied with any thing the Parliament can doe, untill they have received it as the word of God, if it be <hi>jut divinum,</hi> it ought to be aſſerted, not by many, but by all.</p>
            <p>As for Mr. <hi>Gillespies</hi> exception againſt Mr. <hi>Colemans</hi> word bias, &amp; aſſerting they came biaſed for the truth, that is <hi>petitio prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipii,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113335:11"/>and deſerves no anſwer. The ſecond rule: <hi>let precepts, held out as divine inſtitutions,</hi> have <hi>cleare Scriptures:</hi> that is the rule, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> would not adventure to ſay any thing: a <hi>phraſe upon the by; a thing named; are too weake grounds &amp;c. when men may probably conclude different wayes.</hi> Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> doeth not deny that which by neceſſary conſequence is drawn from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to be a divine truth, but ambiguous Scriptures, decided by a vote, if truth, (for they may poſſibly be errors) are but <hi>huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no jure;</hi> let it be prooved, that the <hi>major</hi> part of an Aſſembly have an infallible gift of finding out ambiguous truth, and putting the ſtampe of divine authority upon their determinations. For my part, I wiſh much fearching the Scriptures were put in practice, which cannot be done but in Schooles of Divinity: men truſt more to the opinion of piety, they can purchaſe by their Oratory, their places of truſt, their votes in aſſemblies, then the ſtrength of argument, but of that heereafter. He finds theſe words, let the Scriptures ſpeake expreſly, in Mr. <hi>Colemans</hi> ſecond rule, not ſo, it was out of his rule; he explaneth his rule ſufficiently, to take into it neceſſary conſequences: and for ought I know, the word expreſly, if extended, after a Rhetoricall liberty, to ſignifie plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, apparently, may include what is apparently <hi>in praemiſſis,</hi> though in a moſt criticall ſenſe, that may not be ſayd to be expreſſe, that is not found <hi>in terminis:</hi> but grant, that the word had beene too ſtrait to put into the rule, he put it not in there; but by way of amplification, if expreſſe in Scripture, all muſt bow, he ſayth not till then, how neceſſarily ſoever it may be collected out of the Scripture, they ſhall not bow.</p>
            <p>He reprehendeth Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> for ſupercilious paſſing over in a Sermon, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. without anſwering the arguments of the Learned, upon thoſe places: and in a tract of purpoſe, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth none of thoſe learned arguments: for my part, I ſay with Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> and if ſuch learned arguments, ſuch plenty, it behoved Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> to have cited them; Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> might have taken more paines, then he ſhould have thankes, in finding out ten or twenty arguments, and yet be told at laſt, that he had concealed the weightieſt, he had confuted the arguments in urging them: you ought to have the urging your owne arguments your ſelves, and you can demand no more, but anſwers for your arguments
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113335:11"/>when you bring them. I am of Mr. <hi>Colemans</hi> minde, that one good argument to prove a Church cenſure, or officer, either from the Scriptures, or elſewhere, would doe me more good, then all I have ever ſeene. If Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> will affoord us any that be good, I ſhall returne him thankes for the benefits I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, or otherwiſe, in a brotherly way, return ſuch anſwers as his arguments ſhall require. In the meane time he confuteth Mr. <hi>Colemans</hi> ignorance, that he doth not finde any coordinate go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, but he meaneth ſupreame; hee doeth not meane the coordinate government of an Admirall and Generall, both under a ſuperiour: parents and maſters, all governed by ſuperiours, and no way coordinate: the maſters government ſuperiour to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in his owne houſe: as for the maſter and captaine in a ſhip, the one he ſayth, governeth the mariners, the other the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: and ſo the King of France and Spain are coordinate over their ſeverall ſubjects.</p>
            <p>He ſayth the Miniſter is puniſhable by the Law of the Land: heere is the difficulty: if the Miniſter and Elder have power gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Chriſt, to cenſure all Chriſtians, and they uſe this power, according as Chriſt hath committed it to them; what is the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate above theſe officers? and can he make lawes to bound and limit the lawes of Chriſt? or if they have power to binde, may the magiſtrate looſe? if they uſe this power, may the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian magiſtrate puniſh them? this were to allow Chriſt a very meane kingdome; that his owne ſubjects ſhould controll him: but you will ſay, if he commit any thing worthy confiſcation of goods, or life, or liberty, the magiſtrate may inflict it upon him; but if he attempt to doe it unjuſtly, he is ungodly, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Elders will excommunicate him, and their coordination maketh them their owne judges. As ſoone as the magiſtrate ſhall but diſtaſt any of their actions, preſently he is ungodly, and ſend him to Satan, and then what party the eloquence of the Clergy may find againſt the magiſtrate, if he ſhould go about to reſtrain them, let wiſe men judge.</p>
            <p>It is the thing it ſelf he ſpeaketh againſt it is true: but he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the third rule, and Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> ſaith, Lay no more burden of government then Chriſt hath laid upon them, which is none at all: and his reaſon is, becauſe they have other work to do, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113335:12"/>ſuch as will take up the whole man; to this argument Mr. <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lespie</hi> maketh no anſwer at all, though Saint <hi>Paul</hi> uſeth the very ſelfe ſame argument, to diſcharge the Preachers from overſight of the poore, Act. 6.2. God forbid we ſhould leave the care of the word of God, and ſerve at tables; though the government of the Church, and examination of crimes, both in private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, and in the claſſes, muſt either be ſleighted, or it muſt take up ten times as much time, as the care of the poore; and if government doth belong to them, the care of the poore muſt likewiſe belong to them: but he telleth us, neither the Miniſter can keep himſelfe, nor the Ordinances pure without Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call government, and proveth it not: <hi>he excludeth Elders from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> he told you before he found no inſtitution, of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Church officer: you ſhould have proved the inſtitution, <hi>The Elder that ruleth well is worthy of double honour,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.17. proveth not inſtitution of an officer in the Church, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by this reaſon: the word Elder is either <hi>prima,</hi> or <hi>ſecunda notio;</hi> if <hi>prima notio,</hi> then yee muſt be content with his owne naturall ſignification, and in that ſenſe it is apparently ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the 1 and 2 verſes of the ſame Chapter, where he oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the elder to the younger, and reckoneth elder women and younger women; ſo that if the elder men be officers, I know not why the elder women ſhould not be officers likewiſe: but if this elder be <hi>ſecunda notio,</hi> or <hi>vox artis</hi> or <hi>ſcientiae Theologicae,</hi> ye muſt finde out his definition in the Scripture, how ſhould man know what <hi>genius</hi> and <hi>ſpecies</hi> were in Logick? what <hi>perpendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum, centrum, diameter,</hi> were in Mathematicks without their definitions? if therefore an Elder muſt ſignifie an officer, hee muſt have definition in <hi>Theologie</hi> that muſt be demonſtrative in Scripture: the word Rule is too generall if it be not referred to knowne principles of nature, as a Father, a Maſter, a Civill Magiſtrate; the firſt is a governour by nature, the ſecond by pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate contract, 3 by publicke conſent of the people: and ſuch ye make the Church officer, for ought I know, ariſing out of the conſent of the people; and ſuch governours were called Elders of the Tribes, and our Parliament men and governours are ſuch Elders ariſing out of the publicke conſent of the people; yea Kings and all Civill governours ariſe out of the ſame principle
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113335:12"/>of publique conſent: which power doth ſtill remaine in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, to make choice of their company, and to erect private ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters at pleaſure, to determine the differences that ariſe amongſt them, with conſent; remaining ſtill ſponſable to publique Laws, if they ſhould call one another to account, as 1 Cor. 6. where Saint <hi>Paul</hi> blameth them, for going to Law, and willeth them to ſet up a wiſe man to judge their differences, and that in Civill, not in Eccleſiaſticall matters, which is a difference no man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth: I challenge the Aſſembly; nay, all the World, to bound <hi>cauſas Eccleſiaſticas à civilibus:</hi> for my part I have ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed on that diſtinction this 30 yeares, and never finde any thing of plaine dealing in it, but non-ſenſe, and fraud, the only diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that I could finde, that the proceeding of the Civill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate did pretend to be legall and regular; the Eccleſiaſticall as far as they durſt, to be illegall, irregular and arbitrary, all the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is in the officers that bind, and looſe whom they liſt. I dare not leave this, leſt I ſhould be challenged for not dealing reverently with Scripture; binding and looſing muſt have a ſenſe; I ſay, binding and looſing is meant by preaching of the Goſpell, which none yet durſt deny to be one of the keyes: and the other let him prove that can: though theſe keyes were never given to any of the Apoſtles, but to <hi>Peter;</hi> and he opened the doore of Gods Church to the Gentiles, which was never ſhut ſince, but ſhall ſtand open day and night continually, Eſay 60.11. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy gates ſhall be open continually, they ſhall not be ſhut day nor night, that men may bring unto thee the forces of the Gentiles, and that their Kings may be brought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And may not theſe exhortations be ſtill ſeaſonable? have fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity and keepe company with none but good, and ſuch as ye may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ered by: and doe not goe to Law one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er your differences to ſome honeſt, wiſe men, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine; and that without ſetting up any new government; an arbitrator is no magiſtrate: but ſuch as by force can put his judgements in execution, he only is a magiſtrate. Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> ſayth, Church government diſtinct from civill, maketh an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilable difference betweene the Miniſter and the Magiſtrate, as two governments muſt needs do. Mr. <hi>Gillespie</hi> ſuppoſeth two governments muſt needs be, and then chideth with the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113335:13"/>and with Mr. <hi>Coleman;</hi> but letteth it alone without an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> falleth upon an argument againſt govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, committed to Miniſters taken from feare of ambition, and here he ſpendeth many words, about the words which Mr. <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> alludeth only unto; which I will not trouble my Reader withall: that Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> in plaine tearmes aimeth at is; ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to be feared in Miniſters, and ſheweth what great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation hath been for this cenſure of the Church, that ſome have preferred it before all acts of piety; and have ambitiouſly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, that all ſhould paſſe through their fingers; and that this cenſure hath plunged the world in blood this many hundred years. Mr. <hi>Gillespies</hi> anſwer to the matter of ambition, is only by involving the Civill Magiſtrate in the ſame danger of ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Now is this a good argument, government is neceſſary, but he that is imployed therein hath great temptations to ambition, therefore the Miniſters of the word muſt be enſnared in the like temptation? that they may both conteſt one with another, and ſo imbroile the world in bloud, as the Popes have done, or elſe both joyne together to enthrall the people, as the Biſhops in the Courts of Princes? and not rather in regard that government doth naturally lift up the heart of man, and therefore Miniſters have the name of ſervants, and Lordſhip, and Dominion over the ſlocke denied them in Scripture, to keep them from the like temptation, that they may the more freely from God warn them that are in authority, that they take heed of that temptation: I am confident if this Aſſembly had ſtooke cloſe to their commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which they received from Chriſt, which was to preach the Goſpell, and ſpent themſelves wholly in matters of doctrine, and told the Lords of the duty of their place, to doe juſtice in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without reſpect of perſons, and put the Commons in mind of all their wholeſome Ordinances, that they looke to carefull performance of them, without turning their thoughts after go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; the Reformation had gone on much faſter, and more comfortable then it hath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Coleman ſaith, <hi>That Church government hath diſquieted all the world in the hand of the Pope, and his Clergy, in the hand of the Archbiſhop of Canterbury. Mr.</hi> Gilleſpie <hi>telleth him, That theſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113335:13"/>ſtories are not a little beſide the warke: he ſhould have told what hurt is had done in France, in Holland, in Scotland, in Reformed Churches.</hi> I anſwer, it was the ſame cenſure that raiſed the Pope ſo high, but it grew not to that height in one age: a young Lion will not bite; and you boaſt that your Churches are according to Primitive times; well what they will come to, after times will ſee: we are beholding to the Presbytery for throwing downe the Biſhops, if they caſt away their ambition with them, and take Mr. <hi>Colemans</hi> advice, and ſet up Schooles of Divinity, and move the Parliament for due encouragement; you ſhall then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be men ſeeking the things of Chriſt, and not your own: but of this more by and by.</p>
            <p>A word or two about that place, 1 Tim. 5.17. the Elder that ruleth well, is worthy double honour: from hence two ſorts of Elders are proved, an Elder that ruleth well, &amp; he that laboureth in word &amp; doctrine: here two Elders are mentioned; but the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence whether officiall or perſonall, is very doubtfull; one office may comprehend both theſe duties, and the compariſon may lye in their perſonall excellencies, one may excell in the governing part of the office, and the other perſon in the doctrinall part; one may heare the cauſes and differences of his brethren well, and yet be but a dull preacher: another may preach excellent well, and yet be an unpatient and peeviſh judge: or not to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance your Eccleſiaſticall government ſo farre: the Scripture hath theſe effects, it is profitable for doctrine, reproofe, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, inſtruction; one Miniſters excellencie may lye in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring in doctrine and inſtruction, and this may be his that laboured in word and doctrine: he that reproveth and corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth may be ſaid to rule, and then there is no place for your Lay-elders: but if this place doe ſet up your Lay-elder, and the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is in two diſtinct offices, that here is an Elder that doth governe, and doth not preach; then preaching and governing be the differences, and differences be convertable with their ſubjects: ſo that if one doe governe, and not preach; the other muſt preach and not governe: and this agreeth plainly with the 1 Pet. 5.3. not as governing the flock, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>nique ut dominautes,</hi> not as Lords: for my part I know not how Lordſhip and government doth differ one from another, <hi>dominus</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:113335:14"/>and <hi>dominari,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, be denominatives: he that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneth is a Lord, and he that is a Lord governeth: to imagine that ambition and pride, injury and oppreſſion, or any ſuch vice, did neceſſarily belong to a Lord, is very injurious unto the very title and honour of a Lord.</p>
            <p>That more reckoning hath been made of this dominion, then acts of piety: to this Mr. <hi>Gillespie</hi> ſeemeth to adhere, that all the reſt is worth nothing without this: further occaſion will be given to ſpeake of theſe things.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> doth deſire doctrine, and wiſheth the Civill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to take Government: Doctrine is committed to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the word, by Commiſſion from Chriſt, Mat. 28. and that Commiſſion is to laſt to the end of the world: this Mr. <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> had reaſon to challenge as due from Chriſt, not the Church: but to the Miniſters of the word, the Church hath no where po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to preach the Goſpell, but the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſors unto the end of the world: and therefore, as before he had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, that the preaching of the Goſpel would take up the whole man, eſpecially in our time: our knowledge of the Scriptures is to be acquired by ordinary means, tongues for the language, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe and art for the argument, that the word might be preached in the demonſtration, and argument of the Scripture, and not in the enticing words of mens wiſdome: well might Mr. <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> call for Schools of Divinity, that there might be unity found among the Preachers of the Goſpell; nothing more conducing to unity, then the continuall exerciſe in Schooles: the very people complaine, women, and ſuch as are well minded: why do not you Miniſters meet, and diſpute it out among your ſelves, one teacheth one thing, and another another thing, and we are much troubled and diſquieted by it: there is uſe of Schooles, or otherwiſe it would never be ſet up in Univerſities: <hi>Paul</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted daily in the Schoole of one Tyrannus: Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Parliament that this would advance Religion, more in ſewer years, then ſince the Reformation. Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> cannot but confeſſe, that this would bee a means to make a learned Clergie, but it ſeemeth more good will come by diſcipline, than by all that: and to let us know that learning and maintenance may be without purity of Religion, he inſtanceth in the Jeſuits:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113335:14"/>it is true, when men have their judgements foreſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>led by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt education, and they employed, as the Popes vaſſals to bee ſerviceable to his, and their owne ambitious ends, they have all their learning and endeavours poyſoned: but yet it may be ſaid for the Jeſuits, that we have our Comments from them, and our books are very mean, and not ſavouring of that induſtry which theirs doe; if we had taken the ſame courſe to maintaine the truth, that they have to maintaine their errors, their mouths had long ere this been ſtopped, and the world had beene as full of good books in defence of truth, as now it is with their poyſoned labours: but they ſhail riſe up in judgement againſt us in the day of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Had learning flouriſhed amongſt us as it might have done, ſuch hereſies and diviſions as we now languiſh under, had never appeared amongſt us: our Sermons had not beene ſo full of words and empty of argument as now they are: all men vent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their owne private opinions, ſcarce two men found that ſtate any Queſtion in Divinity alike, all becauſe Miniſters are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with one anothers arguments and opinions, untill they vent them among the people, 1. Cor. 14.29. Let the Prophets ſpeake two or three, and let the other judge: where ye ſee the Prophets muſt vent their opinions, firſt among the Prophets, and not among the people: what they preach among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ought to be digeſted among themſelves, by argument from the word, not carried by vote; where <hi>major pars ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe vincat me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorem:</hi> for Chriſt Jeſus gave his Commiſſion to all the eleven jointly, and their ſucceſſors, unto the end of the world; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though they were guided by an infallible ſpirit, yet Gal. 2.2. Paul came up by the ſpirit to Jeruſalem, with Barnabas and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, and communicated the Goſpell that he preached among the Gentiles, leſt he had run in vaine: much more are we bound to uſe all meanes to preſerve the unity of the ſpirit: nay, wee have no authority to preach, without the approbation of all that are in the commiſſion, by authority of Chriſt: if any ſhall object that it is unpoſſible Miniſters at this day are of ſo many mindes, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, it is a judgement fallen upon us, for that we have not uſed the meanes, nor doe know one anothers minde, and every man taketh upon him to make himſelfe a Prophet, and be judge of his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113335:15"/>owne gifts; or which is worſe, make the people judge, and give them power to make or chooſe their Paſtor: from which principle, the Independents build all their Indepency: yet the Presbyters many, nay for ought I can learne, upon debate in the Aſſembly, the Independents have gained, that the people have right to chooſe their Miniſter: I am ſure Mr. <hi>Herle</hi> for want of skill, and Theologicall diſputations, hath granted it them: and then no reaſon can deny them Independent Church governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if any ſuch thing be as Church government: as long as there be no Schooles, nor men, and matters, are not ripened there, the granting of a falſe principle is not very dangerous: few men can finde the fallacy; a Rhetoricall Sermon, and an Aſſembly vote will mend all; but a falſe principle is moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſeduce the moſt diſcuſſive and knowing people.</p>
            <p>I am confident this one principle hath made all men of parts, and honeſty, Independents, that are ſo; and were I ſatisfied that the people might elect their Miniſter, I ſhould be Independent my ſelfe, though as I now ſtand affected, I thinke it the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive opinion, both to humane ſociety, and ſound religion; moſt contrary to the doctrine of the Goſpell, the mind and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Chriſt, as was ever broached ſince the Sun ſhone: as I am confident, if Schooles of Divinity were ſet up over all the Kingdome, in the Claſſes, and nothing but doctrine medled with, or ſuch things as are in Scripture handled in a School way, would be made appeare unto the greateſt defendents of that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion; they would finde their quaint epithets, and fine figures, their apt ſimilitudes and dainty alluſions, would make no ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmes: your plauſible Preachers, that fill the world with theſe ſtirres, cannot endure the Schools; they wil tel you that Schools will ſpoile Preachers, beſt Schoolemen, worſt Preachers: Schooles will fill the world with controverſies and fallacies: they will tell you of Jeſuits and Papiſts, and what not, to keepe off Schooles. But truth is, nothing but ignorance bringeth in diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of opinions, and men may be very near and plauſible Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, yet very ignorant: and his opnion and applauſe he hath gotten with the people, maketh him bold to vent ſome new opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and then defend it who can, for he cannot: he can preach it, and Print ſomething for it, but for a concluding argument, he knoweth not what to make of any ſuch thing.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:113335:15"/>
            <p>As for thoſe arguments againſt Schooles, that many School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are bad Preachers, it is <hi>fallacia accidentis, non cauſa pro cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa:</hi> ſo few men have skill of argument, ſo little uſed in preaching, that the Schooleman will not take paines to preach: I mind ſuch few men as are noted for famous Schoolemen, whereas if all men were both exerciſed in Schooles and Pulpits, Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies would be ſilenced, and Pulpits filled, with ſuch ſtrength of argument out of Scripture, that tradeſmen would keepe their ſhops, and coblers their ſtalles, and not adventure to get up into the Pulpit: whereas now they ſee that the uſing of alluſions, and phraſing Scriptures, no otherwiſe then men may doe with na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall wit, and a little diligence will performe, and this hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to turne Preachers: and if they ſhould be ſilenſed by force, they would thinke themſelves wronged; but call them to their exerciſe, they will leave of themſelves, and fall to their old imployments.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> is very zealous for keeping ordinances pure, though he hath not, nor ever will be able to proove, that any man by his ſinne, can pollute the Sacrament to any other, but himſelfe. But if they might, cannot men of any ordinary educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if honeſt, be competent judges of ſuch offences? but the Miniſter muſt be called from his Study to examine Drunkards, and Whores, and ſuch notorious offences as theſe, as if none were fit to meddle with ſuch matters but he. He adviſeth the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to give Chriſt his due; I hope they will be commanded that, but what that is, he cannot, or will not proove; we muſt content our ſelves with a little ſauce of Rhetoricke; <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid Gen. 14.23. <hi>That I will not take from a threed to aſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e latchet, and that I will not take any thing that is thine, leſt thou ſhouldſt ſay,</hi> I <hi>have made Abraham rich.</hi> But no Logicke to prove government to be eſtabliſhed by Chriſt in the Church different from civill.</p>
            <p>The argument of the covenant is too low to be thought on in this Diſcourſe: we are now in an higher region, then the words of the covenant; we are about Gods word, we hope there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the covenant contrary to Gods word; if there be, that muſt be thought on in another conſideration: we may not leave enquiring into the word of God, for feare of the oath: this were a point equall to the higheſt of Popiſh tyranny.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:113335:16"/>
            <p>The fourth rule, <hi>A Chriſtian Magiſtrate is a Governour in the Church.</hi> Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> denieth not this. I know not if the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrate governeth in the Church, what uſe there ſhould be of any Governour beſide him. I thought that the Church ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no officers in it, but ſuch as Chriſt had ſet up, had ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted elders, by the appointment of Jeſus Chriſt: and that by your opinion Chriſt had beene the King of the Church, and had ſet up his kingdome, and ſet officers in his Church, and thoſe had been officers in the Church, which Chriſt had appointed in it, and none other: if the Church be Chriſts Kingdome, ſurely ſuch as governe in it, muſt receive commiſſion from him, under the ſame apprehenſion, as he is King, which is as he is Mediator: their commiſſion to governe in the Church, muſt be in this forme: Chriſt the Mediator, King of his Church, doth appoint Kings, and civill Magiſtrates to governe under him, or otherwiſe they cannot governe in the Church, if the Church be the Kingdome of Chriſt, for it cannot be imagined, that Chriſts Kingdome is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any mixture, as humane governments are; if Chriſt be a King, he hath Lawes, not out of the conſent of the people, but he can and doth <hi>dare leges,</hi> unto which all the world is ſubject, Rom. 2.16. Judge all the world according to my Goſpel. 2. Theſ. 7.8. Jeſus Chriſt ſhall come with his mighty Angels, in flaming fire, rendring vengeance on them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpell of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; the Goſpell is the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſt, and the law by which Chriſt will judge all the world: if all the world be under the law of Chriſt, then the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt muſt needs reach over all the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt at his reſurrection declared mightily to be the Son of God, Rom. 14. Act. 2.36. Let the houſe of Iſrael confeſſe, that God hath made the ſame Jeſus, whom yee have crucified, both Lord and Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> confeſſeth, That this day have I begotten thee, in the 2 Pſalm is to be underſtood of the ſtating him in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which he prooveth out of Act. 13.33. If ſo, ſee, in the 2. Pſal. 8. Aske of me, and I ſhall give thee the heathen for thine inheritance, and the uttermoſt part of the earth for thy poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Where ye ſee, God giveth unto Chriſt, all the earth for his inheritance: and further commandeth Kings to ſerve him: and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113335:16"/>therefore is called under the appellation of the Lambe, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can agree to Chriſt but only as a Mediator, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; and in 1 Tim. 6.15. our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is ſaid to bee the only Potentate, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; Jeſus Chriſt be names that agree to him only Mediator.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Kingdome of Chriſt is as ample as his Propheſie; but the Propheſie of Chriſt is extended to all Nations, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the Commiſſion, Goe teach all Nations: the doctrine which they muſt teach commands: now commands have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies power and authority annexed to compell obedience; or otherwiſe they are but vaine commands, verball, and fruſtrate.</p>
            <p n="4">4. No calling can admit the appellation of pious, and godly which is not under Chriſt; and this is that enrichment of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of 1 Cor. 1.5. where hee telleth them they were enriched in all things in Chriſt, and v.30. Chriſt is ſaid to be made unto us wiſdome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, and redemption: no holineſſe without Chriſt; all our holineſſe doth conſiſt in our obedience to Chriſt: if therefore Kings may bee called holy, if their offices may be accounted holy offices, or not ſinfull, they muſt be held off, and under Chriſt, without whom they cannot be pleaſing to God, Pſ. 72.11. All Kings ſhall fall downe before him, all Nations ſhall doe him ſervice: upon which <hi>Calvin</hi> hath theſe words, <hi>In eccleſia &amp; grege Chriſti eſſe regibus locum ques hic David non exarmat gladio, nec diademate ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liat, ut admittat in eccleſiam: ſed cum ſua dignitate venturos eſſe dicit, ut ſe coram Chriſto proſternant:</hi> Kings have place in the Church and flocke of Chriſt, whom <hi>David</hi> here doth neither diſarme of their ſword, nor ſpoile of their crowne to admit them into the Church: but ſaith that they ſhall come with their dignity, and caſt themſelves downe before Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That office which Chriſt hath declared to be of God, and bounded and limited in his Goſpell, that office is held under Chriſt as mediator; but the Civill Magiſtrate is ſo, Rom. 13.4. he is the Miniſter of God, a revenger to execute wrath on them that doe evill; thus far Chriſt hath to doe with the Civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, to declare the minde of God concerning him, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand every ſoule to be ſubject to him; here is as much, and more from Chriſt, then Mr. <hi>Gillespie</hi> will ever finde out for his Church
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113335:17"/>officers for all the Scripture of the New Teſtament came from the Propheticall office of Chriſt; and he was promiſed at the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Law, Deut. 18.15. and thus Peter Act. 3. and Stephen Acts 7. preached: and John 4.25. the woman of Samaria knew that the Meſſia ſhould teach all things: what Paul preached was in the name of Chriſt, for he was a veſſell to carry the name of Chriſt before the Gentiles, and Kings, Acts 9.15. if Kings are not beholding to Chriſt for their offices, they are for the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of their ſubjects, without which the office of a Civill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is little worth.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Civill Magiſtrates office, and Chriſts office, both Kingdoms over the ſame ſubjects: either the office of the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors Kingdome is ſuperiors inferior, or coordinate, I leave to any Chriſtian to determine; but it may be it will be anſwered that the Civill Magiſtrate and Chriſt are converſant about divers kindes of objects, though they be the ſame perſons that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt, and the King; yet it is in divers conſiderations, to divers ends, and by divers means, for the ends, Chriſts ends and the Kings ends are both one, 1 Tim. 2.2. that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life, in all godlineſſe and honeſty, as for divers means that the officers of the Church uſe when that cenſure or Church government which is talked of, is proved out of 1 Cor. 5. Mat. 18. or any place of Scripture, it ſhall be anſwered God willing.</p>
            <p>I paſſe by Mr. <hi>Gillespies</hi> buſineſſe of the little ewe lambe, that he would have kept, I ſay let the ewe lambe alone. It argues no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and therefore I anſwer nothing: But Mr. <hi>Coleman can finde no other government inſtituted, but Civill, and this is laid</hi> to him as a great careleſſeneſſe, that ſought no better into the Scriptures then ſo: Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> hath found in many places the inſtitution of the Church officers, he findes that more ſubjection and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is commanded as due, not only to civill, but ſpirituall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, to thoſe that are over us in the Lord, 1 Theſſ. 5.12. Mr. <hi>Gillespie</hi> ſeeth more then the text yeeldeth, here is no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of obedience at all, here is know them, and eſteeme them highly: but there is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is tranſlated over you: but <hi>Paſſor</hi> telleth us that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with a genitive caſe ſignifieth <hi>pracedo,</hi> and then it ſignifieth no more but them that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113335:17"/>goe before you, either by doctrine or example, here is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of inſtitution: whatſoever this perſon that is to be belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, he is ſuppoſed, not inſtituted in this place, the ſubject is ſuppoſed, not handled in any ſcience: love and honour is due to the Preacher of the Word, who is ſaid to goe before them they teach: but what is this to government? Heb. 13.7. Remember them that rule over you, there is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is <hi>ducum,</hi> them that lead you, here is not obedience, nor ſubjection, but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and imitate their faith: yea but in the 17 verſe, there is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey and rule over you, but that is (as before) them that lead you, the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is no more but be perſwaded: I deny not but it is often tranſlated obey, but it commeth from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is <hi>perſuadeo</hi> to perſwade. <hi>Paſſor</hi> telleth us, it is <hi>verbum forenſe,</hi> a word whereby the advocates perſwade the Judges; I hope ye will not ſay when an advocate by pleading Law, doth perſwade the Iudges, that the Iudges doe obey the advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate: but let the word ſtand as it is tranſlated (yet when it is ſo rigorouſly wrought upon, it cannot be enforced, interpretation belongeth not to the diſputant) Obey: yet is it not alway cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rellative to the command of a ſuperiour: obedience is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times founded on the authority of the ſuperior, ſometimes on the good and benefit of him that doth obey, without any colour or claime of ſuperiority or government: ſo the patient obeyeth the Phyſitian, ſo that maſter that imployeth a cunning work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, muſt be ruled by his workman; yet neither the one, nor the other claime government over his patient or workmaſter: and upon this ground the Holy Ghoſt requireth obedience here, not by an argument from the authority of him that leadeth them, but from the benefit that commeth to themſelves, for that is unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for you, Rom. 12.8. The argument that Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> draweth hence is not out of the place, but the interpretation of the place, and therefore nothing in confutation of Mr. <hi>Coleman;</hi> for he did not ſay he found no inſtitution in <hi>Gualter</hi> and <hi>Bullen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> but in Scripture, though <hi>Gualter</hi> and <hi>Bullenger</hi> are for Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> as <hi>Beza</hi> confeſſeth, whatſoever they ſay upon the place, Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> ſhould prove inſtitution of Church government out of Scripture, the diſputant may not interpret that is the anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers part, as before.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113335:18"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> ſaith, Chriſt hath placed Magiſtrates in his Church, for which he citeth 1 Cor. 12.28. Eph. 1.3 laſt verſes, to prove all government given to Chriſt, and Chriſt as Mediator: I have proved this a truth: though I have left out thoſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> doth confute in anſwer to Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> becauſe I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeake in his juſt vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them.</p>
            <p>Having recited Mr. <hi>Colemans</hi> words, he argueth againſt them <hi>ab incommodo, He cannot upon theſe grounds</hi> aſſert the authority of either Heathen or Chriſtian Magiſtrate. For the Heathen Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, I ſay let Baall plead for himſelfe: but it will be eaſier for Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> to prove the Heathen Magiſtrate unlawfull, then for Mr. <hi>Gillespie</hi> to vindicate him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is ſin for a man to be an Heathen, and ſuch for which Chriſt will come, rendring vengeance in flaming fire, becauſe they doe not know God, nor obey the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt, 2. Theſſ. 1.8. If any man ſhall ſay that Heathen doe know God, let Chriſt confute him: No man knoweth the Father, but the Son, and he to whom the Son will reveale him, Matt. 11.27.</p>
            <p>And for his government, if ſin be lawfull, it is lawfull: for whatſoever is not of faith is ſin, Rom. 14.23. If yee ſpeake of <hi>jus humanum,</hi> and uſurpation in humane eſtimation: this is out of the queſtion. But I wonder a Chriſtian ſhould doubt, whether it be the duty of all men to be Chriſtians, and that it is ſinne in them that are not, which yet it were not, if it were lawfull for them to enjoy their Heathen condition. Joh. 16.9. The Holy Ghoſt when he is come, will convince the world of ſin, becauſe they beleeve not in me, ſayth our Saviour: <hi>Quod malum in ſo non poteſt eſſe modaliter bonum:</hi> That which is evill in it ſelfe, cannot be circumſtantially good. If to be a Heathen be ſin, to governe as a Heathen cannot be good.</p>
            <p>Next, is a blow given to a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, becauſe the brother muſt proove a Deputyſhip, or Vicegerentſhip by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from Chriſt; I conceive he hath commiſſion from Chriſt to be Gods inſtrument to puniſh the evill doer, and doe good to him that doth well: againe, hath any Magiſtrate commiſſion to be Chriſtian, or may they be Chriſtians, and not obey Chriſt? I conceive the Prophets are good Expoſitors of the condition of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113335:18"/>Chriſts Kingdome. Pſ. 72.11. All Kings ſhall fall downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, all Nations ſhall ſerve him. Eſay 60.12. That Nation and Kingdome that will not ſerve thee ſhall periſh.</p>
            <p>But I follow Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie, God and Nature hath made Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and given them great authority, but of Chriſt, as mediator, they have it not.</hi> There is the affirmation; ſee the proofe.</p>
            <p>Church officers, ſayth Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie, have their power from Chriſt, as mediator, and they are to manage their offices under, and for Chriſt.</hi> And this he proveth, <hi>for that they doe the duties of their offices, in the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And the duties of Church officers he citeth, fowre: 1. <hi>come together:</hi> 2. <hi>Preach:</hi> 3. <hi>baptize:</hi> 4. <hi>excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate: and all theſe are done in the name of Jeſus, but the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is not to performe any part of his duty in the name of Jeſus.</hi> And for all theſe he bringeth places of Scripture, to proove the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative, which I ſhall endevour to examine according to lawes of diſputation.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, <hi>in his name we meet together,</hi> Matt. 18.20. <hi>We,</hi> ſayth Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie, meet:</hi> and urgeth it to proove the inſtitution of Church officers; he maketh ſhort worke of it, but weake, no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument. The Text ſayth, when <hi>two or three are gathered together in my name, I am in the midſt:</hi> It ſayth not they are Church offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, neither doth it ſay, none ſhall gather together in my name, but Church officers, or I am in the midſt of none but Church offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers. Well, I excuſe Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> if he ſee no inſtitution of the Church officers out of that place, and I hope ſo will all men, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> himſelfe, upon due conſideration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In his name we doe preach;</hi> that is out of the queſtion: of other governments, I <hi>find no inſtitution,</hi> ſayth Mr. <hi>Coleman:</hi> he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not of the commiſſion to preach, and therefore let that go.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>In his name we baptize,</hi> Act. 2.38. <hi>be baptized in the name of Ieſus,</hi> Act. 19.5. Theſe places he citeth, to proove we baptize in the name of Ieſus, as mediator, as excluſively to Father, and Holy Ghoſt, (leaving out the words of the commiſſion Matt. 28. <hi>baptize in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt</hi>) for ſo the ſtate of his queſtion doth require; for he diſtinguiſheth acutely, and accurately, betweene Chriſt as Mediator, and ſecond perſon in Trinity, in all this argument: and ſo abuſeth theſe places to proove, that we muſt baptize in the name of Chriſt, excluſive to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113335:19"/>the other perſons of the Trinity, which is contrary to the words of the commiſſion, and the practiſe of all Churches: but this is quite out of Mr. <hi>Gilleſpies</hi> buſineſſe, which is to proove other go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment inſtituted beſides civill.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In his name we excommunicate; this is to the purpoſe: proove that Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> 1. Cor. 5.5. <hi>to deliver ſuch a one to Satan:</hi> he maketh great haſte, no more adoe, but we excommunicate: heere is no argument; deliver to Sathan is not to excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, at leaſt they be different termes; which rules of diſputation will not allow. But grant that it were excommunication, and that Paul did excommunicate, as in plaine termes he did deliver to Sathan Hymineus and Alexander, 1 Tim. 1.20. ſo in this place being well viewed it will appeare, that St. Paul ſaith, I <hi>have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed in the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, with the power of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to deliver ſuch a one to Sathan.</hi> The decree was Pauls, and not the Corinthians, though it might poſſible have been an act of the Corinthians, yet no way appertaining unto you, I mean under the notion of a Church, and yet officers of the Church is a terme ſomewhat more remote; and yet ſtill far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt of all from inſtitution: for grant Paul had in termes ſaid, let the Elders of the Church excommunicate, yet he had not inſtituted, but ſuppoſed an inſtitution, this might have proved an <hi>eſſe,</hi> not the inſtitution <hi>niſi remote.</hi> Thus have I examined his argument by rule. Give us Schooles of divinity, that wee may no more be troubled with ſuch arguments.</p>
            <p>But let us further examine what theſe <hi>mediums</hi> (or ſome of them) will yeeld being cloſer put: Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> doth appropriate the meeting in the name of Chriſt, to the officers of the Church, and that is his <hi>medium</hi> to prove their inſtitution from Chriſt, as Mediator: we muſt come for the clearing of this point, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what it is to doe a thing in the name of Chriſt: it is true, much uſe is made of this comming together in the name of Chriſt, in the argument of generall Counſells; but this priviledge of comming together in the name of Chriſt appropriate to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in a generall Councell, our Learned will not allow. Mr. <hi>Whittaker, Quis ferat cos ſic loquentes, dum quae communiae ſunt omnibus Chriſtianis ad paucos reſtringunt,</hi> who can endure them to ſpeake ſo while they reſtraine thoſe things to a few, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113335:19"/>to all Chriſtians? where you ſee he will not endure theſe two or three to be underſtood of Church officers, but of any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. But let us ſee what he ſaith, it is to be gathered in the name of Chriſt: he ſaith,</p>
            <p>To bee gathered in Chriſts name,
<note place="margin">In Chriſti nomine congregari due ſignificat: Primum eos qui con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniunt eſſe veros &amp; ſinceres Dei cultores, &amp; ſanae Religionis profeſſores, quam non aliunde niſi Scripturae didiſcerunt, nam qui alio modo Deum colunt quam quo ille coli vult, quantumvis max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>insi praeſules fuerint in eccleſia, non tamen in Chriſti nomine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregantur: ſecundum ut eo animo conveniant, ut Chriſti mandato per omnia obediant, ut que eas ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum affectiones afferant, ea ſtudia eas voluntates, quae pios Chriſti miniſtres deceant ut nihil propter Dei gloriam quaerant, aut ſibi proponant, ut veritatem ex Scripturis inquirant, inventam aliis commendent, non ut ſuum regnum ſtabiliant, &amp;c.</note> ſignifieth two things: 1. That thoſe that come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are true and ſincere wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of God, and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the true Religion, which they have not learned elſewhere but from Scripture: For who ſo worſhip God any other way then as he will bee worſhipped, though they bee great Prelates in the Church, yet are not gathered together in Chriſts name. 2. That they come together with that mind, that they may obey the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, that they bring with them thoſe affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thoſe deſires, thoſe inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which become godly Miniſters of Chriſt. That they ſeeke or propound nothing to themſelves beſides Gods glory, that they ſearch for truth in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and having fonnd it, commend it to others, not for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing of their owne Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Thus far I hope ye will agree that others beſides Church offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, may be qualified to meet in the name of Chriſt: firſt, that they may be the true worſhippers of God, that they may learne to worſhip God according to his will out of the Scriptures, they may have good affections to obey Chriſt, they may ſeeke Gods glory, and not the ſetting up their owne Kingdome: I hope the Parliament is ſo gathered, and Chriſt is amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Biſhop <hi>Mourton</hi> ſaith, to bee duly gathered in the name of Chriſt, is with ſincere hearts to invocate him, and to ſubſcribe to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113335:20"/>his revealed truth; this may bee done by others beſide Church officers; and I hope our Parliament doth ſo.</p>
            <p>But ſee cleerely out of the Scripture, that a thing may be ſayd to be done in the name of Chriſt, or of God, when men doe any thing in confidence that God will aſſiſt us: ſo Pſal. 20.5. In the name of our God will we ſet up our banners, in confidence God will aſſiſt us: thus I hope the Parliament, and other Chriſtians may undertake the buſineſſe in the name of Chriſt, in confidence of Chriſts aſſiſtance, as mediator, for whoſe ſake the worke they are employed about, ſhall be acceptable to God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in the name of Chriſt, a thing is ſayd to bee done, that is done in the authority, roome, and place of Chriſt, as if Chriſt ſhould doe it himſelfe: and thus officers of the Church, Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> would have act, under Chriſt, and none but they. And this, if granted, will not proove a Church government, ſeeing a man may preach in the name of Chriſt, and yet not governe in the name of Chriſt; for preaching is the worke of Chriſt as well as government.</p>
            <p>But as mediator, Chriſt hath given no ſuch power and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Magiſtrate: and this hee prooveth, becauſe Chriſt hath none to give, as Mediator he would not judge, therfore he had no civill power, Luke 12.14. To this ſo farre as the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: it doth not follow that becauſe Chriſt was not a judge, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu exercito,</hi> therefore the originall right of government was not in him: and this objection may be anſwered thus; Chriſt did not ſay, he was not a judge, but who made me a judge? how doeſt thou know that I am a judge? and thus Chriſt in the time of his humiliation did often hide the manifeſtation of his power: and as for Joh. 18.36. My kingdome is not of this world, I know not how it argueth more for Church government then for civill: as if thoſe governments that ſhould be executed by Church offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ſhould favour leſſe of the world then the civill government: but he falleth to an admiration, as if the thing were unpoſſible, that the power which Chriſt hath received of his father, ſhould be derived to the civill Magiſtrate, but no reaſon to ſhew the wonder.</p>
            <p>He confeſſeth that Chriſt <hi>as he is eternall God, doth with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Holy Ghoſt, reigne over the Kingdomes of the earth: he that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113335:20"/>is the mediator, being God, hath of God all power in heaven and earth, and this power was given,</hi> Matt. 28.18. <hi>both by eternall generation, and declaration at his reſurrection.</hi> Theſe be phraſes that doe aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh me, that any thing ſhould be given to Chriſt, as God, if gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it had beene robbery to have taken without leave; but any thing ſhould be given him that ſhould concerne his Godhead at the time of his reſurrection, is more monſtrous: but let be, if this place bee underſtood of the power that Chriſt hath as ſecond Perſon in Trinity, and not as Mediator, then he had no authority as Mediator to ſend his Apoſtles: for by this authority, hee ſent forth his, Apoſtles to preach the Goſpell; and if that were not the authority that was given him as Mediator, than ye have loſt your commiſſion, which ye ſo much boaſt of, and had not ſo much as the right to preach under Chriſt as Mediator: All au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is given me in heaven and earth, goe yee therefore and preach: from this authority here ſpoken of, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the authority to preach the Goſpell; now it is moſt cleare that he had authority to preach the Goſpell as Mediator, as I have formerly proved.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Gillespie</hi> ſaith, <hi>That hee that is the Mediator being God, hath power to ſubdue his Churches enemies</hi> but as Mediator, hee hath no other Kingdome, but his Church, as God and as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, thoſe be termes ſtrangely oppoſed the Mediator cannot be conceived but as God and man; and that Kingdome which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to the ſecond Perſon in Trinity, cannot be ſaid to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Chriſts, but is the Kingdome of God, becauſe <hi>opera Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad extra ſunt indiviſae:</hi> but the Kingdome of Chriſt is admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by him, whilſt he is at the right hand of the Father by the power of his Godhead: Chriſt the Mediator doth many things as God, which could not be performed by man, and many things performed by the humane nature, which were not agreeable to the divine: it became us to have a Mediator perfect God, and perfect man, and accordingly in the ſtate of humiliation Chriſt, did work as God and man, he wrought his miracles, healed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, commanded windes and ſea, and did manifeſt his divine power by knowing the hearts of men, and now in the ſtate of glory: ſhall he have one Kingdome as Mediator, and another as God? as Mediator is uſed in an ambiguous ſenſe, let it be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken plaine, as Mediator hee worketh as God and as man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> both
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113335:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:113335:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113335:22"/>which actions are actions of his perſon, <hi>per communication<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Mediator is not a third nature, either he doth what Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> entendeth as God, or as man, the natures are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, hee doth nothing as Mediator, which he doth not as God, or as man, or as man aſſiſted by God in more then an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manner; ſhall the Mediator be ſpoyled of his Godhead to ſet up a ſuppoſed Kingdome in the Church, different from the civill? <hi>He that is the Mediator being God, hath power to ſubdue his, and his Churches enemies, and to make his foes his footſtoole; but as Mediator he is only the Churches King, head and governour:</hi> why doth Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> ſhuffle thus? why doth hee not ſpeake plainly, and make his oppoſitions cleare, <hi>ad idem?</hi> and ſay, as Mediator he hath no ſuch power, as Mediator he is God, but it ſeemeth God without power to ſubdue his enemies.</p>
            <p>But when he had affirmed that Chriſt is King, head and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of his Church only (where is couched <hi>fallacia plurium interrogationum,</hi> the word head in a more peculiar ſenſe, may bee aſcribed to the Church, then King, and governour) he proveth that it is ſo, by branding thoſe that deny it with Pho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inianiſme; but if that be erronious, here <hi>Deodate</hi> upon Ezek. 1.26 ſpeaking of the likeneſſe of a man, ſaith it was the Son of God, head of the Church, and King of the univerſe: and Rom. 10.12. by his death and reſurrection, hath gotten him a title to be Lord over all men. And <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the Eph. 1.20. <hi>Sedere fecit in dextrae; dextra non locum, ſed poteſtatem ſignificat; quam pater Chriſto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulit, ut ejus nomine Coeli, &amp; terrae imperium adminiſtret;</hi> he made him ſit on his right hand, right hand doth not ſignifie place but power, which the Father beſtowed on Chriſt, that in his name he might rule heaven and earth: and after, <hi>Cum dextrae Dei coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, &amp; terr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> impleat, ſequitur regnum Chriſti ubique diffuſum,</hi> for as much as the right hand of God doth fill heaven and earth, it followes that the Kingdome of Chriſt is ſpread all over. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt as mediator ſitteth at the right hand of God, his Kingdome as mediator is extended over heaven and earth.</p>
            <p>Again, all mankind loſt not only dominion, but all right to the uſe of the creatures, and Chriſt as mediator is made heire of all things. Heb. 1.2. where the ſtate of Chriſts mediation, his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall, Prieſtly, and Kingly office, are at large ſet out, his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113335:22"/>to a lower condition then the condition of Angels by death: and after is exalted: and in the chap. 2.8. thou haſt put all things in ſubjection under his feet, in that hee put all things under him, he left nothing that is not put under him. I hope no man dare ſay, that he was made lower then the Angells as the ſecond perſon in Trinity: now if hee had ſpoken of Chriſt as mediator, that in that reſpect he had been humbled, and exalted in another reſpect, to wit, as the ſecond Perſon in Trinity, all things had been put under him, the antytheſis had not beene <hi>ad idem.</hi> Againe God is ſaid to put all things under him, whereby it is implied that all things were not under him, before they were put under him, but as the ſecond Perſon in Trinity; ſo nothing could be ſaid to be put under him, becauſe they were in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect alwaies under him: And laſtly, nothing is excepted from this ſubjection, 1 Cor. 15.28. the Son alſo himſelfe ſhall be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to him that put all things under him, ſo Chriſt hath domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over all things, they are put under his feet in ſuch a condition, in ſuch a conſideration, as he himſelfe is ſubject to God, but in the conſideration that Chriſt is the ſecond perſon of Trinity, ſo he is not inferiour to God the Father, therefore he hath not all things put under his feet as ſecond Perſon in Trinity.</p>
            <p>Phil. 2.8.9.10. being found in faſhion as a man, he humbled himſelfe, and became obedient to death, even the death of the croſſe; wherefore God alſo hath highly exalted him, and given him a name, that in the name of Ieſus every knee ſhould bow; you ſee he that was in the forme of a ſervant, was exalted under that deſcription, and ſo high that every knee ſhould bow to him: but as ſecond Perſon in Trinity, hee was not found in the forme of a ſervant, but as mediator, ſo he was God in the forme of a ſervant.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> hath a diſtinction between, dignity, power, and kingdome, but proveth only a <hi>poſſe,</hi> that ſuch a diſtinction is conceiveable, and may be found in earthly Kings, but a <hi>poſſe ad eſſe in Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, non valet conſequentia:</hi> but here I further note that Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> in the cloſe of his brotherly examination, when hee commeth to apply this his diſtinction to the mediator; he ſaith, <hi>as mediator he exerciſeth acts of divine power, and omnipotencie over all creatures in the behalfe, and for the good of his Church, and reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113335:23"/>or diverteth, or deſtroyeth all his Churches enemies,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the 43 page, he denieth any ſuch working to belong to Chriſt as mediator; but as God, whereby yee may ſee how weake theſe grounds are; and how ſmall a matter it is for a Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torician to forget himſelfe in the following of an argument.</p>
            <p>There remaineth now that ſomething bee ſaid in vindication of Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> from the charge of miſ-application of two Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>hee citeth to prove civill govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Church;</hi> unto which Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> ſaith, <hi>firſt if by go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments in that plate, Civill Magiſtrates were underſtood,</hi> yet that place ſaith not, that Chriſt hath placed them, then <hi>à foreiori,</hi> you diſclaime by that means any government in this place as officers under Chriſt. I thought Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie:</hi> would not have let goe the hold he hath under Chriſt, for his Church governments from this place ſo eaſie: Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> need not trouble him falſe about proving that they were put in the Church under Chriſt: I hope if in the Church they will be content to be Chriſts Vicars, or elſe if Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> will be ruled by me, ſo as Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> will not urge this for conſtitution of Church governments, hee ſhall let it goe. God hath placed governments in his Church, and if they be meant civill governments, hee hath gotten thus much, that civill governours are in the Church by Gods appointment; and then I hope Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> will not deny the roome that God hath given them in the Church, upon this ground that God hath nothing to doe to place them there, they ſhould have come in by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Hee brings an argument out of <hi>Calvin,</hi> becauſe the Apoſtle ſpake of ſuch governments as the Church had at that time, but the Church had no civill Chriſtian Magiſtrates at that time; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>major</hi> of that argument wanteth proofe, that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of ſuch officers as were in the Church in his time only: that cannot be proved; I ſhall urge ſome few arguments to the contrary: the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> will not enforce is, ſeeing that word will ſignifie <hi>propoſuit</hi> or <hi>decre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> as well as <hi>poſuit,</hi> he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and that may take in, not onely ſuch officers, the preſent ſtate of the Church did affoord, but alſo hoſe as ſhould hear caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by Gods appointment, come to the Church: and this is plain
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113335:23"/>that in ſundry places the word doth ſo ſignifie, as Joh. 15.16. I have ordained you, that you ſhall goe and bring forth fruit, Act. 19.21. Paul purpoſed, both made by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, yet both are referred to time to come: and then that which you tranſlate pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, may be rendred, he hath appointed to his Church the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution referred to the providence of God, when he ſhalbe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to affoord his Church the enjoyment of theſe ſeverall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments and gifts: for it is plaine, there is in that catalogue, ſome ſuch as the Church ſhall not alwayes have; and why not ſome alſo, which at that time the Church had not? This cannot be a catalogue of ſuch officers as are at all times neceſſary to the Church; for then Apoſtles, might not be mentioned; becauſe the Church is, and long time hath beene without them, as work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of miracles.</p>
            <p n="2">2. At that time there were workers of miracles, which did ſupply the defect of civill Magiſtrates, which is to workt upon naturalls, to induce men to attend upon the means, Act. 8.6. And the people with one accord gave heed unto thoſe things which Philip ſpake, hearing, and ſeeing the miracles which he did.</p>
            <p>Thus much a nationall covenant, and civill Magiſtrate, may require of the people, that they will attend upon the meanes, out of naturall principles, <hi>Deum eſſe, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> in the maner of which worſhip, ſo farre as concerneth the externall education: from youth, and tradition, inſtruction of parents, and humane lawes, are the foundations and the bounds of nationall and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique worſhip: and upon this ground the Iſraelites were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to reach their children the Law of God; and God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into covenant with the father, for the child, as with Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham: and the ſame obligation lieth upon Chriſtian parents to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct their children, Eph. 6.4. <hi>And you fathers, provoke not your children to wrath: but bring them up in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urture and admonition of the Lord.</hi> Which yet they might not, if the doctrine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell might not be received of the father, for the ſon, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther might not require of his ſon the forme of doctrine.</p>
            <p>Saint Paul calleth the doctrine of the Goſpell, Rom. 6.7. a forme: God be thanked ye have obeyed the forme of doctrine, that was delivered unto you, 2. Tim. 1.13. Hold faſt the ſo me of ſound words which thou haſt heard of me: this is called <hi>fides quo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:113335:24"/>cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dimus,</hi> and this may be the obligation of humans ſociety: and God, and Chriſt, and Scripture, may be agreed on by naturall men, even as Idolaters ſet up their worſhip; yet if the Scripture be received for the rule, there is a ſound forme of words, and he that heareth and beleaveth, and obayeth from the heart, ſhall be ſaved, though the Magiſtrate and Miniſter ſhould drive on to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique and ambitious ends, yet the beleever ſhall bee ſaved; and this is the aſſiſtance and helpe the Church can have from a civill Magiſtrate: and how great a mercy is this to Gods people when all incouragement ſhall be given to the preaching of the Goſpel? when the luſt and riot of a people ſhall be reſtrayned by the civil Magiſtrate: men that refuſe to heare the word puniſhed in their perſons and eſtates, and thereby for feare of the Magiſtrate bee brought to the meanes, God muſt judge of the ſucceſſe, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe give it. Compare this with the contrary motions of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, by fire and ſword to ſuppreſſe the Goſpel, and then ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be not indeed helps to the Church, which though thoſe times wanted, yet God appointed that after ages ſhould have; and in the meane time did cauſe men to attend to the meanes by miracles. I have proved that the people were inclined to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to doctrine by miracles, which moveth naturall men to flock together to ſee ſtrange things: if a mount chancke come and tell people be both medicines of ſtrange operations, to cure and kill, to wound and heale, how will people flocks together to heare and ſee ſome ſtrange thing? <hi>eſt natura heminum novimtis avids:</hi> I have likewiſe ſhewed you that people may and ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive God, and Chriſt; and Scripture, by publique conſent: and whatſoever it received by publique conſent is an act of humane law, and to be acted by the civill Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>Now God doth not worke miracles, but to ſupply defect of naturall meanes, when they are wanting: Chriſt cured, when Phyſitians could not: maketh wine of water when they had no wine: provided Manna, when they were in the wildernes, and wanted proviſion, which coaſed when they enjoyed the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Land. When the Goſpell was firſt, and nations were not converted, then miracles were neceſſary to cauſe attention: but after, when nations were converted, which Chriſt ſent out his Diſciples to doe, with all ſpeed, then there will be no uſe of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113335:24"/>miracles: attention and uſe of meanes may be agreed upon, the effect of them every man is concerned to looke to for his owne ſalvation: and happy are we if we can enjoy the meanes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Inquiſitions, and faggots, and bloud.</p>
            <p>And to looke nearer into the Text, to ſee that this was but an appointment, and not a preſent execution: lye have not heere a continued catalogue, but ye have theſe interruptions, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, all theſe might be preſent, and liable to view: then ye have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and to that ye have annexed miracles: they laſted ſomewhat longer then the Apoſtles and Prophets: and laſt ye have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and theſe may be ordinary gift: healing, if diſtinguiſhed from miracles, is an ordinary gift: ſo are divers tongues; and there remayneth no more but helps, governments, and what theſe helps are, <hi>Calvin</hi> confeſſeth he cannot tell: hee thinketh they were ſome officers the Church hath loſt: men are mightily troubled for want of officers, but being put both in one caſe without any conjunction copulative, why they may not belong both to one thing, and this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> may not have ſome influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the times and after age; ſeeing this catalogue is <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>additum eccleſia,</hi> and the gifts mentioned, not limited by their ends, but onely noted as different gifts, to note that all have not the like qualifications: but in Eph. 4.11. there when the Apoſtle ſetteth downe officers, as meanes to the ends which in actions and moralls have a great influence upon the nature of the thing: he leaveth out helps and governments, and reckoneth only fowr: Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, and Teachers; all but Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers imployed about the word it ſelfe, the foundation, penmen of the word, no more left to us but the Teacher, and he alone with the helpe of the labours, of the Apoſtles, Prophets, and Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts; for without them they can doe nothing: yet there this poore teacher is left alone to perfect the Saints, to performe the worke of the Miniſtry, to edifie the body of Chriſt: heere is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther helpe, nor government, yet all theſe things done without them.</p>
            <p>Beſides in that very place where S. Paul by an induction doth demonſtrate that God hath appointed diverſities of gifts, rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koneth all the reſt, and skippeth over helpes, governments, and leaveth them wholly out, which of neceſſity he muſt doe where
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113335:25"/>he was in his induction to deale with their experience, if none ſuch were to be found at that time, they might tell him you aske us whether all be helps and governments, we ſee no ſuch thing; we are ſo far from thinking all governments, that we finde none at all, but why otherwiſe they ſhould be left out I know not ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they did cleereſt ſet forth the difference that one member hath from another (eſpecially to naturall men) which was S. Pauls argument, and therefore I thinke there were none then.</p>
            <p>He hath two other arguments to ſhew the miſ-application of this text, but are trifles not worth anſwer.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the catalogue of Church officers.</p>
            <p>The Magiſtrate is behinde the Miniſter.</p>
            <p>Next he citeth Eph. 1.21, 22, 23. to prove that all govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is given to Chriſt, and to him as mediator, and Chriſt as head of theſe, is given to the Church: Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> ſaith this place maketh more againſt him then for him; ſomething for him by your confeſſion, is the Scripture contrary to it ſelfe, in the ſame place <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con, The Apoſtle ſaith not that Chriſt is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Church a head of all principalities and powers: The brother ſaith ſo, and in ſo ſaying, he maketh Chriſt a head to thoſe that are not his body. 1 Is This a very nice exception, the text ſaith plainly that the power of God ſhewed it ſelf in Chriſt; 1 in raiſing him from the dead. 2 In ſetting him at the right hand of God, which <hi>Calvin</hi> expoundeth</hi> to ſignifie the power which the Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon Chriſt: and further ſaith that theſe words of the 21 ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e far above principality is an <hi>exegeſis,</hi> explaining the right hand of God, the words are, hee ſet him at his owne right hand far above principalities, &amp;c. but in 22, he gave him to bee head over all things to his Church; he ſaith not head over principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but all things; here is great cauſe of exception, here is farre above principalities, but not head; here is head of all things, but not principalities: may not hee that is farre above be called the chiefe or head; or may not he that is head of all things, bee well called head of Principalities: it is true, diſputations doe require men to keep cloſe to termes; but in Col. 2.10. ye have the very words, head of all principalities and powers; <hi>the brother is to blame for ſaying ſo: why may not the brother</hi> ſpeake, as St. Paul ſpeaketh; but it ſeemeth the Commiſſioner will confute St. Paul
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113335:25"/>
               <hi>inſo ſaying, hee ſhall make Chriſt head of them that are not his body.</hi> Well the Commiſſioner will not have Chriſt head of any but his body, then I truſt he is not head of your Presbytery, for then he muſt be head of many that are not of his body; for howſoever men may by rules of charity have the eſtimation of members of Chriſt, yet certainly Chriſt is head of none but his elect; no vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church can challenge the priviledge of being the members of Chriſt, every faithfull man may, but the viſible Church can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; I deſire this may be proved, that unbeleevers and hypocrites are members of Chriſt. If in the viſible Church if Chriſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as head of the Church, which doth by his mediation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the graces of juſtification and ſanctification upon the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; ſo the viſible Church is not the body of Chriſt, as having many members that have no life of grace, nor any ſuch growth as is mentioned, Eph. 4.15. in that argument, that government that Chriſt hath over the faithfull, is truly ſpirituall, and not of this world, and of this Kingdome he hath indeed no officers, but his Spirit; all theſe members have immediate union with Chriſt by faith. As for applying that diſtinction of the exaltation of Chriſt in reſpect of honour and dignity; but not his Kingly office to the interpretation of this text, that Chriſt is in more honour then any creature; but he executeth his Kingly office as mediator over the Church only; and the Apoſtle ſaith only he is far above them: he ſaith not he is head or King of them. I hope the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner will have the Holy Ghoſt ſpeake ſenſe, and make the compariſon to bee made in all theſe things that he is preferred in, he ſitteth nearer the right hand of God, then any principality: you will allow that Chriſt is here ſpoken of as mediator, as rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the dead, and ſet at the right hand of God the Father: See what the Apoſtle ſaith; he ſaith, he is above principality, in principality; power, in power; might, in might; dominion, in dominion; power and might are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the firſt is right, the other is power to maintaine that right; thus the words muſt bee underſtood if the compariſon bee artificiall, and a due compariſon. I hope you cannot deny that all theſe in any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, are under the right hand of God, and there Chriſt as mediator ſitteth, and is nearer the right hand of God; in all theſe reſpects, he is above them, but not head: but if this had been to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113335:26"/>be underſtood above in dignity only, that is in eſtimation: only this muſt have beene limited to eſtimation with God, for wee all know that he hath no ſuch eſtimation among many names on earth, which yet hee is above even in their owne greatneſſe, whenſoever he is pleaſed to make uſe of that right hand of God, where he is ſet.</p>
            <p>For that his illuſtration as he called it, it is rather an aberra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the matter in hand, then any thing toward the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of it; our excellencies, dignities and powers are ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivative, and in eſtimation only, that they yeeld us no govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at all; no man can ſo far exceed another as to obtaine go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by his excellencie, without ſome law or conſent of others to beſtow it; this is nothing to the interpreter of the place: if all this had no more but expreſſed the dignity of Chriſt; what need all this accumulation of words, when all might have been expreſſed in this word, Hee is far above all dignities? for though here is a preferring of Chriſt before rights, and powers, and dominions, yet hee hath none of all theſe but dignities, and theſe are all in this world, and that which is to come: if yee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the word World as many doe to make roome for the Church, he hath no dignity there neither: ſo all this majeſty of words commeth to nothing in this world, and in the end of the world he layeth downe all to his Father. But <hi>volens, nolens,</hi> at laſt the Commiſſioner muſt come to it, Chriſt is head of princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities: in the place before cited, Col. 2.10. but that is in another ſenſe, not as he is mediator, but only as he is God: and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles meaning is nothing but this, that Chriſt is true God, doth he not meane alſo that he is true Chriſt, as well as that he is true God? and if Chriſt, doth he not meane that he is mediator? but the Commiſſioner ſaith, that in that place the Apoſtle ſheweth is true God; doth that follow that ſpeaketh not of Chriſt as me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, becauſe he ſpeaketh of him as true God: is not Chriſt true God as mediator? he teacheth the Colloſſians not to worſhip Angells, becauſe ſervants: but may they not worſhip Chriſt as Mediator? yes doubtleſſe they may. Now it is plaine that hee ſpeaketh of Chriſt as mediator, as may clearly appear both in the 9 verſe and beginning of 10 verſe, in him dwelleth the fulneſſe of the Godhead bodily; that in Chriſt the mediator yee are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113335:26"/>in him, that is as mediator: the text ſaith, that he is head of principality and power, that proveth that Chriſt is God, ſaith Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie,</hi> God not mediator? that is no conſequence; yee ought not to worſhip Angells, who are but creatures, becauſe ye are compleat in him that is God; and in him that is better then Angells, and is head over them, therefore not as mediator, but as ſecond Perſon in Trinity? I ſee no conſequence in this col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But it is plainly interpreted in the Colloſſ.</hi> 1.15.16.17. <hi>how Chriſt is head of principality and power:</hi> It is plaine in that place the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh of Chriſt in whom we have redemption through his bloud; that is, as mediator, the image of the inviſible God: that is, we have the knowledge of God made knowne to us in him, Joh. 1.18. that is as mediator, if by communication of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties the creation were attributed to Chriſt as God; is it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore denied to him as mediator? well let the Commiſſioner, <hi>acute Philoſophari do Deo,</hi> and ſay as God and not as mediator, he did create the world, and together with other things did cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate principalities and powers: well, if it be not the office of the mediator to create the world: ſhall it not therefore bee in the compaſſe of the mediators office to governe any thing that was created? now here is a new diſtinction between the perſon and office of Chriſt, what kinde of diviſion ſhall this bee? ſhall this be a lawfull diſtribution of Chriſts actions? ſome perſonall, ſome officiall, thoſe things that prove Chriſt to be God, doe by no meanes belong to the office of Chriſt: he ſaith all this is to bee underſtood not of his governing and Kingly office, but to prove that he is true God: I formerly ſhewed that what doth belong to the ſecond Perſon in Trinity, together with Father, and Holy Ghoſt, and is denied to belong to God man, doth in no ſenſe belong to Chriſt: the perſon of Chriſt is God and man, no conſideration of Chriſt but as God man; nothing can be ſaid of Chriſt as ſecond Perſon in Trinity in oppoſition to mediator, but in oppoſition to man, there may, as before.</p>
            <p>But here ſomething hath the ſhew of an argument, that Chriſt hath two Kingdomes, one as God, other as Mediator, and that is taken from the continuation; hee hath a Kingdome that he ſhall lay downe unto God his Father: there is another that he ſhall
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113335:27"/>retaine together with God the Father, the firſt, he hath over the Church only; the ſecond, over all the world: here is ſomething ſaid, but doth it appeare that the Kingdome that hee ſhall lay downe to God his Father is not over all the world? The laying open of this buſineſſe will ſolve the whole knot, and lay the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity thereof to the view of all the world.</p>
            <p>Chriſt hath a Kingdome which he will lay downe to God his Father, which Kingdom is alſo called eternall, 2 Pet. 1.11. which is underſtood of the Kingdome of grace; for he ſaid, they ſhould make their calling and election ſure; then they ſhould never fall, for ſo an entrance ſhall be made into the everlaſting Kingdome of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus: in this Kingdom he is ſovereigne Lord, to none but thoſe unto whom he is alſo a Saviour: now the word Kingdome is taken divers waies, ſometimes for the ſubjects of the Kingdome, and in that ſenſe, thoſe that are the elect of God ſhall evermore be made ſubject to the government of Chriſt; ſometime for the manner of adminiſtration, and ſo Chriſt in the day of judgement ſhall lay downe all the office of mediatorſhip; and that government by which now, and in the laſt day, not the Church only, but all the world ſhall be judged, Rom. 2.16. God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt, and this is called the Kingdome of Chriſt, becauſe by his media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath obtained from the Father that he ſhall not judge any man according to rigor, but as they are in, or out of Chriſt, all deferring of judgement from the wicked, is in and for Chriſt, which otherwiſe the juſtice of God would not allow; all the admiſſion of us into the preſence of God, is by the humanity of Chriſt, all conveying of grace to us is by Chriſt, he is to us wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, redemption: but when he hath overcome all his enemies, and preſented all his elect to God his Father, and judged all that are out of him to eternall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; then ſhall all that diſpenſation of juſtice ceaſe, which is therefore called the Kingdome of Chriſt becauſe by his Goſpell all ſhall be judged, and by him, and for him, all that reigne for ever with God, ſhall be preſented to him.</p>
            <p>Now this is not ſo to be underſtood, as ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> as if God the Father were idle while Chriſt reigned: that Majeſty which God beſtowed on Chriſt, was not convenient for bare man, but
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113335:27"/>in the nature that he was humbled he was exalted by the Father, and he gave him a name before whom every knee ſhould bow, Phil. 2.9.10. in the government of the world, he is as it were the Vicar of his Father; it cannot be that the Father ſhould be idle, while he is imployed, ſeeing he is the wiſdome of the Father, and of the ſame eſſence with him; but the Scripture doth tell us, that Chriſt hath the government of heaven and earth inſtead of the Father, that wee ſhould not thinke of any other Lord and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour but him, that we ſhould looke for ſalvation only in him; we acknowledge God to bee governour but in the face of the man Chriſt: but then when Chriſt ſhall give up the Kingdome which he hath received, he ſhall not ſpoyle himſelf of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but transferre it from his humane nature, to his divine; becauſe wee ſhall then have acceſſe to God, whither our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity will not now permit us to come; then the vaile being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved we ſhall ſee God reigning in glory, without the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the manhood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now it is true, none are in <hi>pace Domini Regis,</hi> but the Church, nor all them neither, if ye ſpeake of the viſible Church: but ſhall not men be judged by Chriſt, for not knowing God, and for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to the Goſpell? it is plaine, <hi>z.</hi> Theſſ. they ſhall; and the theeves, and diſobedient tranſgreſſours, are under govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, aſwell as more legall, and better ſubjects.</p>
            <p>But grant, that the Kingdome of Chriſt were in, and over his Church only, which will never bee prooved, nor dare I ever grant, but <hi>rethoricè,</hi> yet what is this for your different govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from the civill? Chriſts Kingdome is adminiſtred in <hi>dextra Dei;</hi> and you ſayd Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> muſt proove if the civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate will be but King under Chriſt his deputation, may not the like be required of you, Mr. <hi>Gillespie?</hi> I pray proove any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion iſſuing out from the Kingly office of Chriſt: Chriſt had three offices, his Prieſtly office finiſhed in offering himſelfe: his Kingly office we read how it came to him, ſitting at the right hand of his Father, but any commiſſion for any man to governe under him in that Kingdome, we read none: <hi>Tanta Majeſtas non convenit Chriſto homini,</hi> ſayth Calvin upon 1. Cor. 15. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if the kingdome be ſuch, as man cannot enjoy, it is ſuch, as man cannot execute: and when Chriſt ſayd, His kingdome was not of this world, be ſayth, he had other maner of creatures then
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113335:28"/>men: he could procure many Angels, though one were enough to vindicate that kingdome.</p>
            <p>It is plaine Chriſt did delegate officers, to execute his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall office, and granted a commiſſion to his Apoſtles to laſt to the end of the world; but his Kingly office he executeth, by the right hand of his Father, where he ſitteth at the right hand of the Majeſty on high: his propheſie he executed himſelfe on earth, as a man, and when he left the earth, deputed officers to execute that office in his abſence, till he returne to judge in the laſt day: obedience is due as well to a Prophet, as to a King, nay Kings themſelves ought to obay the voyce of Prophets. Our Saviour telleth the Diſciples ſent but to the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, Matth. 10. That he that deſpiſeth them, deſpiſeth him: if he will beare it, let us content our ſelves. <hi>Paul</hi> was an elect veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to carry the name of Chriſt before Kings, accordingly he doth in the name of Chriſt direct Kings, to doe their offices, as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of God, and commandeth their ſubjects to obey them: the very word inſtrument doth implie, that they are in the hand of God, and therefore though <hi>inſtrumenta animalia,</hi> nay <hi>rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> and ſo capable of an inſtruction, yet if they worke not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the minde of God, the right hand of God will rule them where Chriſt alſo ſitteth in majeſty.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt had three offices, let us take heed how we confound them: the office of his propheſie, is to teach: hee that will not heare the voyce of that Prophet, ſhall die the death: but the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that ſentence of death belongeth to another office, namely the Kingly office, for which Chriſt hath appointed an aſſize, which is called the day of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, 1. Cor. 1.8. that ye may be blameles in the day of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: all tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors are every where bound over, to anſwer their offences before Chriſt at his comming: but ſummons is the act of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall office of Chriſt committed unto us his Miniſters: now what reaſon is it that we preach the neceſſity of their appeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to anſwer all their ſinnes, infidelity, impenitency, before Chriſt, that we ſhould without any commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminer,</hi> take upon us to cenſure theſe that the Goſpell ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before the time come?</p>
            <p>Or if we grant further, that Chriſt hath granted the execution
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113335:28"/>of his Kingly office, to his Church, what is that to the Miniſters? That is nothing to the Miniſters, their worke is not dominion, but by the propheſie, and teaching to helpe ſayth, which the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt hath ſeparated, 2. Cor. 1.24. not that we have domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your faith, but are helpers of your joy. Let any man prove that a Miniſter hath any more to doe from Chriſt, then to teach and baptize, which of neceſſity you muſt if you imploy him <hi>jure divino,</hi> about government. God forbid wee ſhould leave the word of God, and ſerve at Tables: the Biſhops heeretofore did except counſell tables, and you muſt except conſiſtory tables: or certainly, whether they have tables or no, your conſiſtory im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment: for there is as much impediment in that, as in other imployments to preaching the word.</p>
            <p>If then I ſay, this dominion be derived from Chriſt, though you muſt make as hard ſhifts to proove it, as the Pope to derive his authority from Peter: why ſhould thoſe that are the Miniſters intermeddle? why ſhould wee endevour to perſwade men to make uſe of this ſentence of excommunication, to ſet the people of God one againſt another? me thinkes our ayme ſhould be to preach unity. St. Paul did every where preach this unity: and in the ſame Epiſtle wherein, upon occaſion, he preacheth this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, as you will have it, hee beginneth his Epiſtle with an exhortation to unity, among the people, and among the teachers, 1. Cor. 1.10.13. <hi>Now I beſeech you brethren by the Name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that ye all speake the ſame thing, and that there be no diviſions among you: but that ye be perfectly joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame minde, and in the ſame judgement.</hi> For ought I ſee, heere is nothing preached that may binde up the breaches, but as though nothing were intended but diviſion, excommunication is the only ſubject: let us preach unity, a good while, that ſo they may get footing, to excommunicate heereafter, if any ſuch thing doe appeare out of the word of God. If meanes were made for this unity firſt, when we can all agree about excommunication, we may have piety and peace in the injoiment of it: but bleſſed be God, now they be the ſame perſons, the ſame qualifications requiſite to acting in Church and common wealth: why ſhould the ſame man in the field electing a Knight of the Shire, be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt himſelfe, as a Church man, and common wealths
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113335:29"/>man? why ſhould this man chooſing a Knight, act, by other principles then in chuſing an elder? ſhould he make choice of an holy man to be an elder, a wicked man for the Parliament? how much better were it for all men, to comfort themſelves in this, that they doe injoy this Chriſtian liberty, that nothing is layd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them but by their owne conſent (ſo as the conſent of any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſociety can be procured) we are as free in our eſtates, as in our conſciences? and thus Chriſtian liberty is to be underſtood: you are free, 1. Pet. 2.16. is not ſo to bee underſtood, that they ought not to ſubject themſelves to the neceſſary rules of humane ſociety, that Chriſtians might make covenants of ſubjection, as in the election of a member of the Parliament, and then breake that covenant by Chriſtian liberty, or to imagine your ſelves not borne under the lawes of your Country, becauſe Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Thus far you are free by Chriſtian liberty to obey parents in the Lord only: when your naturall parents, or parents of your country commands any thing againſt God, you are the Lords freee-men, God is above them.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be Almighty God, our Magiſtrates profeſſe it is their duty to be guided by the word of God; and happy are we that we have ſuch Magiſtrates: let not us have our liberty as a cloak of malice; why ſhould a Commonwealth bee denied the appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and priviledge of a Church? did Chriſt principally aime at Nations, and put their names only into the Commiſſion? Teach all Nations, under that word comprehending all men, and refuſe any Nation the admittance into the covenant of the Church: what muſt words of a Commiſſion admit of a Rhetoricall ſenſe, and have no literall truth, ſome of all Nations, not the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative body of a Nation? But if the Parliament will give mee leave and ſuch encouragement that I may make it my worke, I ſhall endeavour to make appeare the great miſtake, the name and nature of the Church.</p>
            <p>But now at laſt, Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> hath gotten ground, and adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tureth more boldly upon theſe words, before they made more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, then for him: now not one word in the text for him, before there was ſomething for him, and ſomething againſt him; now not one word for him.</p>
            <p>Verſe the 21 affordeth this argument againſt him: The honor
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113335:29"/>and dignity that Chriſt there ſpeaketh of, hath place not only in this world, but that which is to come: but the government that is given to Chriſt as Mediator, ſhall not continue in the world to come: therefore the government given to Chriſt as he is Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator cannot be meant in that place: This is <hi>ignoratio Elenchi,</hi> a plaine and obvious fallacie, here is government given to Chriſt in this world, and that which is to come; that which belongeth to him in reference to the world to come, belongeth not to him as Mediator, therefore that government that is given to him in reference to this world, is not given to him as Mediator; ſeeing the words doe yeeld this argument, I am glad they yeeld no better. I have already ſhewed the ſenſe of Chriſt laying down his Kingdome to God his Father.</p>
            <p>Verſe 22. He hath put all things under his feet; that is, ſaith <hi>Zanchius,</hi> all things but his Church which is his body; and why muſt the Church bee excepted? Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> could ſee that all things yet were not put under in Heb. 2.8. the latter part of the verſe, but could not ſee the words immediately going before, he hath left nothing that is not put under him: <hi>but the Church is not under Chriſt,</hi> then Chriſt doth not governe his Church: he hath ſo troubled the ſenſe of theſe words, that truly I cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what he meaneth: he citeth 1 Cor. 15.25. he muſt reigne till he hath put all his enemies under his feet; and in Act. 2.34.35. Sit thou on my right hand, till I make thy foes thy footſtool. Now, ſaith Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie, When Chriſt bath put downe all rule, and all authority, and power, and put all his enemies under his feet: then he ſhall ceaſe to reigne as Mediator, but till that bee done, hee ſhall reigne as Mediator: ſo that it can never bee proved, that the meaning of theſe words, hee hath put all things under his feet, is that, all government is given to Chriſt as Mediator.</hi> Here is great ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to finde out a Kingdome for Chriſt, as Mediator over the Church only: and this putting all things under his feet, muſt ſignifie Chriſts Kingdome, after the Mediators Kingdome is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up to the Father; becauſe as ſoone as Chriſt hath put all things under his feet he reigneth as Mediator no longer.</p>
            <p>For anſwer to this argument, I ſay, that untill he hath put all his enemies under his feet in 1 Cor. 15.25. and he that hath put all things under, 27. have not the ſame antecedent; the former, hee is God man, the Mediator: the latter, is God the Father; in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113335:30"/>the ſubject of this ſubjection is his enemies; this latter, all things: the former is an actuall putting them under; this latter, as Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> doth allow out of <hi>Jerome,</hi> is but in decree: put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his feet in the former, is finall deſtruction of death, a putting downe of all rule, authority and power, a confuſion and deſtruction of all his enemies: in the latter, God put Chriſts enemies, under his feet; but under the common condition of all things, friends and foes are put under the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt by God his Father; here he is ſet above princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities, but letteth them alone in their inferior condition; there he putteth them downe, here they are under him, but there hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>keth them quite away; here he receiveth the government of the Mediator, there he finiſheth it: here God putteth all things under Chriſt, Church and all, whatſoever <hi>Zanchius</hi> ſaith to the contrary: there Chriſt, according to the power that is heere given him, putteth his enemies only under his feet: heere God giveth the right in recompence of his ſuffering, as Phil. 2. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God hath exalted him, &amp;c. There hee executeth his wrath upon his enemies: in the meane time he governeth as mediator, and keepeth off the deſtruction from the wicked, and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his people, that they may be blameleſſe in the day of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The next words furniſh Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> with another argument againſt Mr. <hi>Coleman: gave him to bee head over all things to his Church.</hi> I know not how Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> doth finde out his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the words ſtand for Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> ſtill: the gift is given to his Church, or for the helpe and benefit of his Church: but hee was given to be head over all: <hi>he is head over none,</hi> ſayth Mr. <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſpie, but his Church.</hi> Is this to argue out of Scripture, or rather to deny, and outface the Scripture? the Scripture, ſayth he, is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all, for the good and benefit of his Church: what good can he doe his Church, by an empty dignity, without any governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or authority? but if he that hath power over all things bee given to his Church, this is a gift indeed full of comfort to his Church, that he that is head in reſpect of influence and life, is head of all things, or at leaſt over them in government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The laſt verſe doth further confirme what</hi> I <hi>ſay,</hi> ſayth Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie, for the Apoſtle continuing his ſpeech ſayth, which is his body, the fulnes
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113335:30"/>of him that filleth all in all: he calleth the Church Christs fulnes, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to his headſhip:</hi> That ſeemeth tolerably to come from the Text: but ſee the fallacy comming after: that which maketh him compleat, ſo far as he is head or King: how commeth this word King in heere? <hi>Having his Church fully gathered, he hath his compleat Kingdome, his perfect body.</hi> Then as ſoone as he hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his Kingdome, he preſently layeth downe; ſuch a Kingdome ſcarce worth the name of a Kingdome, that exceedeth not the bounds of his owne body, and continueth no longer then he hath got the crowne; for Chriſts body not compleat till the laſt day. This is very great liberty, that Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> taketh in arguing more then <hi>poetica licentia,</hi> to put in King, when it is not in the Text, whence he will ground his argument: Doth not Chriſt, as me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, fill heaven and earth? ſure as mediator he is God, what is he God as mediator, without the properties of God; I never heard of ſuch argumentation: but in the queſtion of tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, there is <hi>accidens, ſine ſubjecto,</hi> and <hi>ſubjectum, fine acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus propriis:</hi> heere is <hi>Deus ſine Deo:</hi> as for his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, glory, power, and kingdome: glory, not derived from a Kingdome, I know none; a kingdome, without power and glory, a nominall empty thing; kingdome, power and glory, is nothing but a compleat Kingdome. Hee telleth us, that Chriſt as Mediator executeth acts of divine power over all creatures in behalfe of his Church, if he hath right to doe it then he is King, I thinke: I deſire Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> to give us ſome deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions of the termes of his diviſion, of kingdome, power and glory; and ſee how by Scripture he can prove how they do agree or not, to Chriſt as Mediator, under his deſcription; and ſee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther how theſe termes may ſerve for interpreting of Scripture, and ſetting up of his opinion. But Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> is very angry with this opinion, that Chriſt as Mediator is King of Kings, and all doe governe under him, and ought to governe for him, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he is ſo much offended, ſure it is not becauſe he would not have Chriſt have ſo much power; nay he is afraid that Miniſters ſhall be deprived of ſome part of the office that Chriſt hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them: by my conſent if Mr. <hi>Gillespie</hi> can prove that any part of government was given to the Miniſters, by Chriſt; no man ſhall queſtion Chriſts title; and I hope our Magiſtrates will not take any thing from us, Chriſt hath given us: I wiſh that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113335:31"/>men would looke impartially upon the word of God, and ſee how it can be proved that Chriſt hath given any government to Miniſters immediately, or whether any to the Church: to give all diſputants and godly men opportunity to deale clearly in theſe points, I wiſh theſe points might be decided among our ſelves in a candid diſpute, rather then to fill the world with our diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences.</p>
            <p>Let theſe be the queſtions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether Chriſt gave any more government to Miniſters then is contained in preaching and baptizing? <hi>Neg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether hee gave any government to the Church at all? <hi>Neg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether Miniſters have any right to thoſe priviledges that are given to the Church more then another Chriſtian? <hi>Neg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether a Commonwealth profeſſing the Goſpell bee a viſible Church? <hi>Aff.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether any member of ſuch a Commonwealth rightly ordered where he hath his conſent to making of Civill Lawes, may hold himſelfe free from ſuch Lawes in matters of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? <hi>Neg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether Miniſters have commiſſion from Chriſt to preach? <hi>Aff.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether the people have any power to chooſe their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters? <hi>Neg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things being candidly diſcuſſed, and we being all of one minde in them, I hope peace may be expected amongſt all the members of the Kingdome,</p>
            <p>Which God grant.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
